<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Peter Ramus, his logick in two bookes. Not onely truely translated into English, but also digested into question and answere, for the more easie understanding of all men. By R.F. Gent</title>
            <title>Dialectica. English</title>
            <author>Ramus, Petrus, 1515-1572.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72513</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15249.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125061</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900357</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900357</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150998</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72513)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150998)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1994:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Peter Ramus, his logick in two bookes. Not onely truely translated into English, but also digested into question and answere, for the more easie understanding of all men. By R.F. Gent</title>
                  <title>Dialectica. English</title>
                  <author>Ramus, Petrus, 1515-1572.</author>
                  <author>Fage, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 107, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Nicholas Vavasour, and are to bee sold at his shop in the Inner Temple, neere the Church-doore,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Ramus, Petrus.  Dialectica.</note>
                  <note>Dedication to Bestney Barker (the uncle of the translator at Saint Gilses in Essex) is signed: Ro: Fage.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Logic --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Questions and answers --  Logic --  Miscellanea --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150998:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150998:1"/>
            <p>Peter Ramus HIS LOGICK <hi>In two Bookes.</hi> Not onely truely Tranſlate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but alſo digeſted into Queſtion and Anſwere, for the more eaſie underſtanding of all men.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. F.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Nicholas Vavaſour,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop in the Inner <hi>Temple,</hi> neere the Church-doore. 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150998:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150998:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL, MY ASSVRED loving Vnkle, <hi>Beſtney Barker</hi> Eſquire, at Saint <hi>Gilſes</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVOrſhipfull Sir, being excited, as well by the bond of kindred, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by your loue and courteſie towards me, to ſhew you ſome thankfulneſſe, withall to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie a reciprocall and mutuall loue towards you againe, not forgetting that duty, which both as a kinſman and friend I owe unto you, I adventured (albeit my beſt ſtrength bee but weaknes) upon a bold aſſay, namely, to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate this worke, and preſent it unto you, as a ſmall mite of that tribute, which even nature bindeth me to render. But ſeeing my firſt worke unluckely ſuppreſſed it ſelfe, I have added unto my former boldneſſe, a more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious part, namely, not onely to tranſlate it againe, but alſo to illuſtrate it according to my ſmall ability, by the plaine and facile way of a Dialogue. May it croude it ſelfe into your preſence and gaine the leaſt aſpect of a favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable countenance, I ſhall thinke my time wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150998:3"/>ſpent, and not onely ſo, but imploy my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout weightier matters. What ſaid (weighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? this Science &amp; Author may ſtand before Princes, if not ſpoiled by my own unſkilfulnes. However it ſhroudeth it ſelfe under your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, vntill the ſtormes of reproch and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominie be overpaſſed, ſoliciting in the meane time a pardon for mee, in that I have preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to offer ſuch a trifle to ſuch a kinſman. So hoping that the worke, though ſmall, may be accepted, and benevolentlie intertained, I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit both it and my ſelfe unto your favourable cogitations in all dutifulneſſe; and reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 26. 1632.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your aſſured loving Nephew <hi>Ro. Fage.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150998:3"/>
            <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>BEnevolent Reader, I doe here preſent thee with this ſmall worke, hoping it may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce good effects. Certainly it hath aſſayed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time to thruſt it ſelfe into the world, but that it found ſo kind friends, who conſidering the unworthineſſe, were pleaſed to ſuppreſſe it and keepe it priſoner in the goale of their owne houſes. Howbeit now it is adventured abroad, and with the spring beginneth to spring afreſh. Its winters impriſonment is likely to better its ſummers condicions, for I have laboured ſo far as I could to prune and loppe off the former er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, that ſo it may be the more plauſible. I have alſo adorned it with a new weed, to wit of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, or queſtions and anſwers, that ſo my booke may even learne to ſtoupe to the weakeſt capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. If it ſhall be thought to come in a new faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may you pleaſe to looke into the world, you may ſee abundance in this habit, our common Catechiſmes weare this gowne; yea, Mr. <hi>St: Egerton</hi> of the <hi>Blacke Friers</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> hath contracted the ſeven treatiſes of Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> into this forme. For my part, I hold it more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie
<pb facs="tcp:150998:4"/>then the former tract, neither greatly preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to the Author.</p>
            <p>This adorned, I have given this my ſecond ſonne, full libertie to be a free-man, baniſhing my firſt and worſt labours, from the view (ſo farre as I can) of all men. For ſeeing it would not, when I would, I hold it not fit, that now it ſhould be publiſhed. Touching that worke, it ſlowed ſo inconſiderately from my penne, and ſlipped ſo raſhly out of my hand, that it eſcaped not without many defaultes, imperfections, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurities &amp; blemiſhes: that with the Egyptian Graſhopper, it will not onely conſume ſome part, but utterly eate up and waſte the golden ſeaſon and happie houres of the courteous reader. Let this laſt worke then kind reader finde favour in thine eyes; if that winter bird ſhould be ſeene, it would appeare like a Cuckoe at Chriſtmas, or like the Oule which is the admiration of other birds. I will onely now ſhew thee the cauſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing this laſt worke, and the uſe thereof, and ſo leave it to thy diſcreet iudgement. The cauſes are manifold, firſt to ſtoppe the ſpringing of that Abortiue foreſpoken off, that ſo it might not thrive to the diſcredit of its parent. Secondly that the gratuity and thankefulneſſe to my Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle aforeſaid might not be buried in oblivion, for <hi>tritum eſt perire quod facis ingrato.</hi> Thirdly, for the benefit as I ſaid of the ſimpleſt capacitie.
<pb facs="tcp:150998:4"/>And finally for the zeale I beare to mine owne country, being willing and deſirous, that not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, but even women, ſhould exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the ſtudy of the ſacred artes.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall demande what benefit ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downd hereby, or what may be the uſe hereof? I anſwere, it will availe greatly, not onely for ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and morall diſcourſe, but alſo for the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of all errors, either in manners or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for ſaith <hi>Ovid,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adde quod ingenuas didiciſſe fideliter artes emollit mores nec ſinet eſſe feros.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But may ſome ſay, I live privatly, converſe not in the world, what neede have I of this ſcience? It ſeemeth to conſiſt chiefly in diſputing, but I imploy my ſelfe most in ſilence and meditation. Well friend, thou mayeſt have great benefit by this ſcience, even in that likewiſe, an example of which, word for word, I have here produced out of Mr. <hi>Egertons</hi> treaty aforeſaid, that ſo thou mighteſt know how to benefit thy ſelfe by this ſcience even in thy meditation.</p>
            <p>What thing is this O my ſoule, that doth ſo beſot thee? or what manner of thing may it bee, wherewith thou art ſo delighted, or rather bewitched, and how doth the Holy Ghoſt in the ſcriptures define it, and ſet it forth? who are ſinners, but they that rebell againſt God, and againſt his holy will, revealed in his word?<note place="margin">Definiti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.</note> and what other thing is ſinne, but a breach &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion
<pb facs="tcp:150998:5"/>of the law of God, <hi>1 Iohn. 3.4.</hi> a tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of the way of life, as the phraſe of the old Teſtament doth import, and a ſwerving from the right marke and end, as the word uſeth in the new teſtament to ſignifie: viz. the glory of God and thine owne ſalvation. This curſed thing called ſinne, is not of one ſort or kind; it is is a monſter of many heads, and (as it were) a beaſt of many hornes. It is both originall, bred and borne with us, and actuall ſpringing out of us from that venomous root of our originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Againe, it is either inward lurking and boyling in the heart; or outward ſhewing it ſelfe in the life and converſation: ſometimes it onely inhabiteth and dwelleth in us, and oft times it doth raigne and overrule us; ſometimes it is but an error and infirmity, and ſometimes it is a willfull and preſumtuous evill, <hi>Pſal. 19.11, 12.</hi> ſometimes it is pardonable, by the free grace and mercy of God to them that truely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and repent; and ſometimes it is utterly unpardonable and never to be forgiven, being ſuch that it is impoſſible that the committers thereof ſhould be renewed by repentance, <hi>Matth. 12. Heb. 6.</hi> Sometimes it ruſheth mediately and directly againſt God, and ſometimes it reacheth more properly to the hurt of our neighbour. But who is able to reckon up all the branches of this moſt bitter and venomous tree, wherefore (to
<pb facs="tcp:150998:5"/>looke more nearely unto it) whence proceedeth this deadly poyſon,<note place="margin">Cauſe Efici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</note> what may be the cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it commeth, and the fountaine from whence it ſpringeth? Surely my ſoule, it is even thy ſelfe: thou art the roote that bringeth forth all this bitterneſſe, thou art the fountaine from whence all this deadly venome doth ariſe. For every man is tempted to ſinne, and hee is drawne away of his owne concupiſence, and enticed. Beware therefore O rebellius ſoule, that thou lay not the blame upon the Lord, neither make him the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of thy ſinne: for thou O God as thou canſt not be tempted to evill thy ſelfe, ſo thou tempteſt no man to commit ſinne, being a thing which thou ſo ſtraitly forbiddeſt to all, and ſo ſeverely threatneſt in whomſoever it is found, and for which thou ſo grieveouſly plagueſt the wicked, and ſo ſharpely correcteſt thine owne children, <hi>Iam. 1.13, 14. Heb 12.7, 8.</hi> Thou O Lord art holineſſe it ſelfe and the fountaine thereof, and there is none eternally, and unchangably good but thee alone, <hi>Mat. 19.</hi> Thou madeſt man good at the beginning, but he ſought many inventions <hi>Eccleſ. 12.</hi> ſo all the imaginations &amp; thoughts f his heart be came onely evill continually, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, ſabboth and all, <hi>Gen. 6.5.</hi> True it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that the Divell that old Dragon uſing the ſubtle ſerpent for his inſtrument, did offer the firſt occaſion of ſinning, wherby he became an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
<pb facs="tcp:150998:6"/>cauſe of ſinne, and is called a murtherer from the beginning, and the author and father of all deceit, <hi>Iohn 8.44.</hi> yet man had power to have reſisted him if he would, which he not doing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the true &amp; proper efficient cauſe of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf, &amp; all his poſterity, who likewiſe by meanes of the poyſon derived from his loynes, became alſo the proper and immediate cauſes of their own ſinnes. Marke well then (O my ſoule) the roote of this evill, and further conſider, what unſavory &amp; curſed fruit it bringeth forth; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly even ſuch as it ſelfe is,<note place="margin">The fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Cauſe, or the end or fruit of ſinne.</note> for ſuch as the tree is, ſuch are the fruites: as is the roote, ſo are the branches; a poyſoned fountaine casteth forth no wholeſome ſtreames, <hi>Iam. 3.</hi> and who can bring (as the wiſeman ſaith) a cleane thing out of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe? ſurely there is not one, but onely hee who is holineſſe it ſelfe, <hi>Iohn 14.4.</hi> And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all controverſie, the reward and wages of ſin is death, and that not onely temporall and bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which is a ſeparation of the body from the ſoule for a ſeaſon, but alſo spirituall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall both of ſoule and body for ever and ever. Is any good thing withheld from us? let us thanke our ſin for it: is any plague or puniſhment laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us? be ſure that ſinne is the cauſe, or at the leaſt (even in the deareſt children of God) the occaſion of it. Is any good bleſſing of God made of no force, or even turned to a curſe to us? wee
<pb facs="tcp:150998:6"/>may be ſure that it is by reaſon of our ſin: for (as the Prophet ſaith) the Lords hand is not ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that it cannot ſave, nor his eare heavie that it cannot heare, but our iniquities ſeperate betwixt us and our God, and our ſinnes doe hide his face from us that he will not heare, <hi>Eſay 59.1, 2.</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) <hi>miſerie ſpringeth not forth out of the duſt, neither doth affliction ſpring out of the earth, but man is borne to labour as the ſparkles fly upward, Iob 5.6, 7.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, man is as prone by nature to ſinne againſt God, &amp; conſequently to pull Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon him ſelfe, as the fire (which is a light element) is naturally prone to aſcend and mount aloft. And to the end that thou (my ſoule) maiſt ſee upon what an ugly monſter thou hast ſet thy delight, doſt dote upon,<note place="margin">The o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſites &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>traries</note> and art bewitched withall, conſider how faire and amiable pietie and vertue are, for as they make a man lovely and honorable, ſo ſinne maketh him loath ſome and contemptible: <hi>The feare of God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>) <hi>makes the face of a man to ſhine and be beautiful,</hi> but impiety and prophaneſſe do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face and diſfigure the image of God in him, and cauſe both God and all good men to loath and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt him as a polluted and filthy thing, <hi>Favour</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Wiſe-man</hi>) <hi>is deceitfull, and beauty is vanity, but the woman that feareth the Lord, ſhee ſhall be prayſed, Prov. 31.39.</hi> A
<pb facs="tcp:150998:7"/>
               <hi>vile perſon is contemned</hi> (that is, a prophane man and baſely eſteemed how great ſoever he be in the world) <hi>in the eyes of him that feareth God, Pſal. 15.4.</hi> And pietie is the onely beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that the Lord himſelfe is delighted with, <hi>1 Pet. 3.4.</hi> Therefore it is cleare in the contrary part, that hee loatheth and abhorreth impietie and ſinne,<note place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> and yet my ſoule to bring thee further out of love with this moſt ugly monſter, conſider whereunto it is like and to what it may be compared. It is like (ſaith <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi>) to filthy raggs, that are caſt aſide upon the dunghill, and deteſted of al the paſſers by. It bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth as a ſerpent and ſtingeth as a Coccatrice, creepeth as a gangrene or deadly canker, that eateth to the heart and cannot bee cured; and though it ſeeme ſweete in the beginning, yet it is moſt bitter in the end, and that which reliſheth like hony in the mouth, will prove ranke poyſon in the bowels.<note place="margin">Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</note> Finally O my ſoule if thou peruſe the holy Scriptures, thou ſhalt find no booke, no leafe, no chapter, no ſcarce any verſe, wherein there is not ſome precept, ſome prohibition, ſome promiſe, ſome threatning, or ſome example which ſeemeth not very fitly &amp; profitably to ſhew forth the amiableneſſe of vertue, and the uglineſſe of ſinne, &amp; with what care, zeale, watchfulneſſe, &amp;c, the one is to be ſhunned, and the other to bee imbraced. Thus farre Mr. <hi>Egerton,</hi> Lib. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Cap. <hi>6.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150998:7"/>
            <p>Now that thou maiſt attaine kind reader unto this ſweete delight of meditation, or to the top of whatſoever felicity thou aymeſt at by this art, uſe my booke in this manner follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>It conſiſting onely of rules and examples, will bee no great burthen for thee to commit it all to memorie, and ſo whether thou meditateſt or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſeſt, of ſinne or piety in the generall, or any vice or vertue in the particular, thou ſhalt finde from the head of this arte after the example foreſhewed, abundance of matter to furniſh thy meditation. So <hi>cum pacis ſapientibus</hi> I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my labour to thy diſcreete and favourable conſtruction, and with equall reſpect to all indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>R. F.</hi> Junior.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150998:8"/>
            <head>PETER RAMVS to the reader wiſheth health.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ARchymedes</hi> (O Reader) would have the reaſon of the ſpheares and clymates (in which invention he had more vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laboured) ingraven upon his ſepulchre. And truely ſhouldeſt thou aske me of my vigils, and ſtudies, I deſire a piller to be rayſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my grave from the inſtructions, of the art of Logicke. Touching the cauſe of the wiſh, they anſwer firſt to the accuratnes of the art, the bookes of invention of arguments, and their diſpoſition to be iudged, not onely from <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> Organicall, Rhetoricall, Phyſicall, but from <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Quintilian,</hi> and ſo many Orators. In all which wee have ſtrived with all ſtudie &amp; diligence, by all reaſonable wayes, to contract them briefly into theſe two books, that no particle, or the leaſt ſhadow of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke might be there confuſed, whoſe truth might not bee expreſly delivered. And this ſhall be firſt made knowne touching <hi>Archy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes</hi> his probleme. They anſwer ſecondly to the uſe of Logicke, the elegance and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of all the parts to be explicated, to ſtirre
<pb facs="tcp:150998:8"/>up logicall meditations, as well the popular phraſes of Poets, Orators, Hiſtoriographers, as alſo the liberall and ingenuous ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of a new body deliuered in a new forme to the ſtudious, adorned with excellent indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and leaſt any ſhould feare leaſt they ſhould happen to be ſtrangers, they are given and committed to the liberall cuſtodies of their School<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. This ſhall be ſecondly made knowne touching <hi>Archymedes</hi> his probleme. Theſe therefore ſhall be witneſſe of ſo many daies &amp; night watches, touching the truth &amp; vtility of Logicke, and ſhall anſwer for the cauſe of our wiſh, ſhall alſo admoniſh thee (reader) as I hope of I know not what mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is in moſt academies of Europe, diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their ſophiſticall precepts, how that they are farre unlike both to the verity and vtility of Logicke, and ſhall alſo inflame thee to the ſtudy of the more true &amp; profitable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties. But beſide this there is obiected a great company, extructed with theatricall reproches, threatning paines of tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall iudgement, condemnation at the leaſt of filthy ignorance and calumny, will thruſt us from the whole kingdome of Philoſophy as ſtrange &amp; unheard of preſcription, both with hands and tongue, whether will they forbid the ſmall cauſe of our wiſh? what freedome
<pb facs="tcp:150998:9"/>was obtained by King <hi>Henry</hi> from the envy of ſo mad a Iudge; to the more ſolide iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a milder cenſurer? what afterward, (when this Logical ardor had ſet foot into the cauſe of religion) was a more great offence, the life and health of us being aimed at by thoſe three civill warres? will theſe ſhew no cauſe of our wiſh? yea rather they doe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh, That we give great thankes to the almighty, who hath ayded and protected the courſe of our ſtudyes hitherto, neither would ſuffer them by any meanes to be interrupted. Therefore I witneſſe that this light of Logick will availe greatly to the ſtudious in ſetting forth the truth, as alſo to adorne the ingenuous artes, as cheifly theilluſtrating the heavenly miſteries of the ſacred Doctrine: I pray that it may grow up more and more to theſe things, and and that this booke may be happily concluded to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of GOD.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150998:9"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE Chapters in the two books of <hi>Peter Ramus</hi> his Dialectica.</head>
            <list>
               <head>In the firſt booke.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> The definition of Dialectica.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The parts and kindes of arguments.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> The Efficient procreant &amp; conſervant Cauſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> The Efficient alone and with others.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> The Efficient by himſelfe or an Accident.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> The Matter. <hi>7.</hi> The Forme. <hi>8.</hi> The End.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> The Effects. <hi>10.</hi> The Subiect.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> The Adiunct. <hi>12.</hi> Diverſes. <hi>13.</hi> Deſperates.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Relates. <hi>15.</hi> Adverſes. <hi>16.</hi> Contradicents.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> Privants. <hi>18.</hi> Equalls. <hi>19.</hi> Greaters.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Leſſers. <hi>21.</hi> Likes. <hi>22.</hi> Diſlikes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23.</hi> Conjugates. <hi>24.</hi> Notation. <hi>25.</hi> Distribution.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26.</hi> Diſtribution of the Cauſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>27.</hi> Distribution of the Effects whether of Kind or Spece.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28.</hi> The Diſtribution from the Subiects.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29.</hi> The Diſtribution from the Adiunct.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30.</hi> Definition. <hi>31.</hi> Deſcription.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32.</hi> Teſtimony Divine.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150998:10"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>33.</hi> Teſtimonies humane of Lawes &amp; Sentences</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the ſecond booke.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Of Iudgement.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Axiomas affirming or denying.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> True and Falſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> The ſimple Axioma.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> The copulate Axioma.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> The connexed Axioma.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> The Diſcreete Axioma.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> The Diſiunct Axioma.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> The Sillogiſme and his parts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> The ſimple and contracted ſillogiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> The firſt kind of the ſimple explicates Sillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> The ſimple explicate Sillogiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> The firſt connexed Sillogiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> The ſecond connexed Sillogiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> The firſt diſiunct Sillogiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> The ſecond diſiunct Sillogiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> The onely method according to <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> The firſt illuſtration of Method by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of artes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19.</hi> The ſecond example of Poets, Orators, and Hiſtoriographers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> The ſecrets of Method.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150998:10"/>
            <head>THE FIRST BOOKE OF PETER RAMVS HIS DIALECTICA of Invention.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 1.</hi> What Dialectica is.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Dialectica?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Dialectica is the art of diſputing well, and in that ſence is called Logicke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 2.</hi> The parts of Dialectica and kinds of Arguments.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many ports hath Dialectica?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Dialectica hath two parts, Invention and Iudgement.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Invention?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Invention is a part of Dialectica of inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Arguments.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Argument?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:150998:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Argument is that which is affected to argue any thing: ſuch as are all reaſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered a part and by themſelves.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the Kindes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Artificiall and Inartificiall.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Artificiall Argument?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That which argueth of it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the Kindes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Firſt, or derived from the Firſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt is that which is of its own original.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the Kindes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Simple or Comparative.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Simple?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Simple is that which is conſidered ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and abſolutely.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What bee the Kindes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Agreeing or diſagreeing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Agreeing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That which agreeth with the thing which it argueth.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the Kindes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Agreeing abſolutely or after a certaine manner.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is agreeing abſolutely?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Cauſe and Effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 3.</hi> The Efficient, Procreant, and Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Cauſe.</head>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150998:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Cauſe?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The cauſe is that by whoſe force the thing is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Profit of it?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>This firſt place of invention is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all knowledge: and hee is beleeved to know, of whom the cauſe is held.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As the Poet ſaith worthily:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The man ſure happy is who cauſe of things doth know.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How is the Cauſe divided?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Into two kindes, Efficient and Matter, or forme and end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Efficient Cauſe?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The Efficient Cauſe is that from which the thing is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How many Kindes hath it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There appeareth to us no true Kindes, yet the great plenty of it is diſtinguiſhed by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine meanes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is that which effecteth by the firſt meanes?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That which procreateth or defendeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give me an example out of ſome Poet?</p>
               <p>A. Ovid <hi>firſt,</hi> remedio amoris.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalt look in this our medſonal Art</l>
                  <l>My admonition doe, ſet Idlenes apart.</l>
                  <l>This cauſeth thee to love, this doth defend it ſtill,</l>
                  <l>This is the cauſe of Ioy, as meat ſomtimes breeds ill</l>
                  <l>Take laſtly ſloath away, God Cupids bow is loſt,</l>
                  <l>His torches loſe their light, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temd away the'r toſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give me a more familiar example?</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150998:12"/>
               <p>A. <hi>The Father and Mother procreate, the Nurſe defendeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give an example of this out of ſome Poet?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>4.</hi> Aeneid.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Th'art no Gods Child, ne Dardanus his ſon,</l>
                  <l>Thou rather from the ſteep hard rocks didſt come.</l>
                  <l>Of Caucaſus: it ſeemeth of that breed,</l>
                  <l>Hyrcanian Tygars thee with breaſts did feed.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeglog. 8.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now what this whorſon love is I well wot,</l>
                  <l>It is a little buſie boy begot.</l>
                  <l>Not of mans ſeed ne ſibb to one of us,</l>
                  <l>But fartheſt Garamants and Iſmarus.</l>
                  <l>Or rockie Rhodope as it ſhould ſeeme,</l>
                  <l>In their rough ragged hills ingendred him.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Doe not builders and governours of Cities come under this head?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Yes</hi> Romulus <hi>the builder of the City of Rome, alſo all other Kings, Conſulls, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors are defenders and keepers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 4.</hi> The Efficient done and with others.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is that which effecteth by the ſecond meanes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That which effecteth alone or with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are thoſe others?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Some oftentimes are Principall, others are helping and Miniſters.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150998:12"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of the Cauſe that effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth by it ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Aneid.</hi> 6. <hi>Niſus</hi> calleth backe both the blame &amp; the puniſhment of the Slaughter from <hi>Enryalus</hi> upon himſelfe: becauſe he was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly author.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lo here I am who only did this deed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Latians, againſt me turne your ſwords with ſpeed;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tw'as my deceit: He could it never doe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ne would his courage ſerve him thereunto.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of the ſolitary Cauſe with Principalls and Fellowes out of ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Solitary cauſe with many both Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalls and Fellowes, is diverſly ſet forth <hi>pro Marcello.</hi> For the warlike prayſes (ſaith the Orator) they are wont to extenuate truely by words, and to detract them from their leaders, to communicate them with many; leaſt they ſhould bee proper to their Commanders: and certainely in warre, the ſtrength of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, opportunity of places, helpe of fellowes, ranks, proviſion do much availe. But Fortune (as it were) by her own right, challengeth the cheifeſt part to her ſelfe, and whaſoever is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperouſly carried, that altogether ſhe leadeth. But yet of this glory (ô <hi>Caeſar</hi>) which a little before thou dideſt obtaine, thou haſt no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: all that, how much ſoever it is, (which truely is the cheifeſt) all (I ſay) is thine. The centurion, preſident, Rankes and companies have taken from thee none of this prayſe: Yea
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150998:13"/>even the Lady of humane affaires, Fortune of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth not her ſelf into the ſociety of this glory, to thee ſhe giveth place, and confeſſeth it all and wholly to be thine.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are not Inſtruments numbred among hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Cauſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this Argument the impious Epicure diſputeth that the world was never made. <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo de Nat.</hi> For by what eyes of the minde (ſaith hee) could your <hi>Plato</hi> behold the frame of ſo great a worke, wherby hee maketh it conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and builded of God? what labour? what iron Ingens? what Lever? what deviſes? what Miniſters were there of ſo great a worke?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 5.</hi> The Efficient by it ſelfe or an Accident</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is that which effecteth by the third meanes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That which effecteth by it ſelf or an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How effecteth it by it ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When it effecteth by its owne faculty.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How effecteth it by its owne facultie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When it effecteth by nature or counſell.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of that which effecteth by Nature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Efficient of the windes is Naturall.</p>
               <p>Aeneid. 1.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150998:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Eaſt and South windes on the Sea doe blow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They ruſh through deep, till on the top they ſhow.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The affrick oft with theſe his blaſts conioynes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſo the floods are caſt up by the windes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give ſome example of that which effecteth by Councell?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That confeſſion of <hi>Cicero,</hi> touching him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, is an example of Councell. The warre ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand (ô <hi>Caeſar</hi>) waged alſo for the moſt part, not conſtrained by any of my Iudgement and will, I came forth to thoſe warres which were undertaken againſt thee.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How doth the Efficient Cauſe effect by an Accident?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When it effecteth by an external faculty.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How doth it effect by an externall faculty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When it is done by Neceſſity or Fortune.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How by Neceſſity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When as the Efficient is conſtrained to to the Effect.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is one in the excuſe of the Pompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians. But to me truly (ſaith the Orator) if there may be ſought out a proper and true name of our evill, it doth ſeeme that we are falne into a certaine fatall calamity, that hath occupied the vnprovident mindes of men; that none ſhould wonder how humane Councell is ouercome by Divine Neceſſity.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How by Fortune?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When ſomewhat happened beyond the ſcope of the Efficient.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150998:14"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So the caſe chanced (ſaith <hi>Tullius tertio de Nat: deo:</hi>) That <hi>Pherius</hi> the enemy was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to <hi>Iaſon,</hi> who opened his impoſtume with his ſword; which the Phyſitians could by no meanes heale.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>May not imprudence bee numbred amongſt theſe kinde of Cauſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Ovid. de Triſt. 2.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Why hurtfull light or ought elſe did I ſee?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The fault way mine and not unknowne to mee.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wiſe</hi> Acteon Diana <hi>Naked ſaw,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And food became to's Doggs devouring maw.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Blind fortune mongſt the Gods is ſurely blamed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ne pardon gets, the Gods ſhee hath ſo harmed.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Doe not Deprecations then proceed from hence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro P. L.</hi> Pardon ô Father: he hath er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: he is ſlipped: he thought not: if ever hereafter. And a little after I have erred: I have done raſhly: it repenteth me: I flie to thy clemency: I aske pardon for mine offence: I intreat thee that thou wilt pardon me.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What firſt cauſed the name of Fortune.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ignorance of the Cauſes hath feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this name: for when as ſomething happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beyond Councell and Hope, it was called
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150998:14"/>by the common people Fortune.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is</hi> Iuvenals <hi>opinion of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Wiſe if we were no God ſhould want but For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: We place thee high and often thee importune.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 6. <hi>The Matter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Matter?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The Matter is the cauſe of which the thing is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give an example out of ſome Poet?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>By this feigned Argument, the houſe of the Sunne is compounded of gold, carbunkles, Yvory and Silver.</hi> Ovid <hi>2.</hi> Mettamorf.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Suns high place was built with pillars tall,</l>
                  <l>The gold did ſhine Carbunkles flames let fall,</l>
                  <l>The top thereof was layd with Yvory neate,</l>
                  <l>And ſilver dores in portall ſhined feate.</l>
                  <signed>Aeglog. 3.</signed>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A merrie Muſor fram'd of beech in tree,</l>
                  <l>Caru'd worke, by hand of divine <hi>Alcimeden,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis round impaled with a ſcattering trayle,</l>
                  <l>Of tender Vine, and over all betweene,</l>
                  <l>A pale greene Ivy, wherewith as a vale,</l>
                  <l>The thick diffuſſed cluſters ſhaded beene.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give an example out of ſome Orator?</p>
               <p>A. Caeſar <hi>1.</hi> Bel. Civil: Caeſar <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded his ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to make ſhips of that kind, which in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer yeares the uſe of the Brittaines had taught him: firſt they made the keyle and pinns of light
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150998:15"/>matter, the reſt of the body of the ſhip being knit together with Oſiers, was covered over with Leather.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 7. <hi>The Forme.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>The firſt kind of the cauſe, in the Efficient and Matter being expounded; the ſecond follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, in the forme and the end; what therefore is the forme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The forme is the Cauſe by which the thing is that which it is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the benefit of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From hence the thing is diſtinguiſhed from all other things, and the Forme is ingene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated together with the thing it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give ſome example of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A reaſonable ſoule is the forme of a man, becauſe by it a man is a man, and is diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from all other creatures thereby. The form of the geometricall figures is in triangles and quadrangles. Heaven, Earth, Trees, Fiſhes are the forme of Phyſicall things. From whence the cheife explication of things, as it is by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo (if it may be found out) it ſhall be as in artificiall things it is more eaſily met withall.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Caeſar lib.</hi> 7. But all the French walls are almoſt of this Forme, the beames long and playne, with equall diſtance betweene them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150998:15"/>two foote, are placed upon the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Theſe are bound within and faſtened very ſtrongly: for thoſe ſpaces (of which we ſpake) are filled up to the top with great ſtones. Theſe placed and knit together, an other rowe is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo added<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the ſame might keepe the ſpaces: neither doe the beames touch one another, but being diſtant by equall ſpaces, all of them are ſtrongly faſtened great ſtones being placed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them. And even ſo is the whole work knit together untill the iuſt height of the wall he fulfilled. This worke therefore is not defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as well for the comelineſſe and variety, beames and ſtones being by courſes which keepe their rowes in right loynes, as, becauſe it hath the cheife ſtrength for profit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Citties, becauſe it doth defend both from the miſcheife of ſtones, and the materiall ram, which with its forty feet, being oft bound to the long beames inward, can neither be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or drawne backe againe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Aeneid.</hi> 1. <hi>Virgill</hi> deſcribeth the forme of his port.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Betweene two ſeas two Iſlandes there doth lie;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sidewayes they'r made, the water runns faſt by.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Huge double Rocks that doe reach up to heaven,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vnder the which the ſeas lie ſtill and calme:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And by the that place green woods there are grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Forth from the ſame comes great blacke darknes flowing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vnder which rock a dens made very fleet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:150998:16"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wherein's rich living ſtones and waters ſweet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Houſes for Nimphs &amp; chaines for ſhips there laid</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which would not by the Ancor or the chaines bee ſtaid</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 8. <hi>The End.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The End is the Cauſe for whoſe ſake the thing is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To Phyſicall things the propoſed end is man to man, God. There is ſome cheife good and laſt end of all artes: as to ſpeake well, of Grammer: to plead well, of Rethoricke: to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute well, of Logicke.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Aeneid.</hi> 1. <hi>Iuno</hi> aſſumeth the end of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage when as ſhe promiſeth <hi>Deiopeia</hi> to <hi>Eolus</hi> to wit for ſolace and childrens ſake.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nimphs full fourteene I have of bodies rare</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But who ſo is moſt beautifull and faire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Even</hi> Deiopeia <hi>I to thee doe give</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Her yeare in Mariage ſtate with thee to live,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thee to reward for thy love unto me,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And cauſe thine of ſpring beautifull to bee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example out of ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cicero pro Lig.</hi> Vrgeth <hi>Tubero</hi> his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, when as he preſſeth the end of the wars ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up againſt <hi>Caeſar.</hi> And truely (ſaith he) he is come forth armed againſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelfe.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150998:16"/>But what did this <hi>Tubero</hi> his ſword doe in the Pharſalian Armie? whoſe ſides did the ſharpe point ayme at? who was to feele the force of thy weapon? where was thy minde, eyes, hands, courage? what didſt thou deſire? what didſt thou wiſh?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 9. <hi>The Effects.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Effect?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Effect is that which ariſeth from the cauſes, whether begotten or corrupted, or whether any thing be moved by any meanes. Here the motion, &amp; the thing done by motion, is called the Effect. Of this place are prayſes &amp; diſprayſes, of which ſacred &amp; Prophane books are full.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of this out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Aeneid.</hi> 6. The facts of diverſe people are compared to the praiſes of the Romans.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some finely carve upon the boyling braſſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They'l on the marble grave a living face,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They wiſh the cauſes better, they'l deſcry</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heavens ſhining parts, and tell the ſtars ith sky,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Remember thou Romes people brave to rule,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe things ſhall be thine art, peace to impoſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſpare thy ſubiects, and ſubdue proud foes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe commeth under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hitherto are ſpeeches and writings referd</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150998:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pericles</hi> and <hi>Hortentius</hi> did celebrate the praiſe of pleading well: and by the ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> &amp; <hi>Cicero</hi> writing wel.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What further?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To this place are referred councells and deliberations, although not brought to their end.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>menio</hi> and <hi>Phylotus</hi> were beaten to death, becauſe they were ſuſpected to be of the conſpiracy againſt <hi>Alexander,</hi> as <hi>Curtius</hi> and <hi>Arianus</hi> have remembred touching <hi>Lentulus, Cethegus</hi> and others, the complices of <hi>Cateline,</hi> they ſuffered puniſhment by iudgement of the Senate.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Have not vertues and vices their Effects alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Horace</hi> after this manner deſcribeth the Effects of drunkenneſſe.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Secrets it ſhews, and hope it doth command,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vnto the wars it drives, although unarmd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It takes the burden from the carefull man,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It teacheth art to all that will or can,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who ere was drunke that wanted Eloquence?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Was any poore that uſed this defence?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 10. <hi>The Subiect.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>The argument agreeing after a certaine
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150998:17"/>manner ſucceedeth, what is that then?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Subiect and Adiunct.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Subiect?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Subiect is that to which any thing is adioined.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Make this playner by examples?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The minde is the Subiect of ſcience, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, vertue, vice, becauſe theſe happen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the being. The body, of health, ſickneſſe, ſtrength, weakneſſe, beauty, deformity. Man is the Subiect of riches, poverty, honour, infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, apparrell, company. The place is the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of the thing placed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>how prove you this laſt by teſtimony and example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Phyloſophers attribute a place to divine beings, although wanting part and greatneſſe. So the place of Geometry and the difference of places is in Geometrical things: ſo of phyſicke, it is more diligently conſidered in phyſicall things: In the world, in ſimple elements, in compound things.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſonte Poet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So <hi>Virgill</hi> in his Georgicks admoniſheth that the place bee diligently ſought out for things propoſed: as come, trees, plants, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Before we paſſe into a ſea unknowne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Know we the wind and various maner of heaven,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our native ſoyle and every habitation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What will refuſe or grow in any nation:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:150998:18"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some beareth corn, th'other with grapes doth paſſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some with tall trees, the reſt with unſowne graſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Proceed further in explicating the ſubiect?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſubiects of ſences are called ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; of vertues or vices things propoſed to vertues or vices.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of the former?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Colour is the ſubiect of the ſight, ſound of the hearing; becauſe theſe ſenſes are occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and exerciſed in the ſenſibles.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of the latter?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Vertues and vices are ſet forth in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall philoſophy by this argument, temperance and intemperance by pleaſure: magnanimity and ſloth, by danger: liberality, and covetouſnes, by riches.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Explicate the ſubiect further?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So things numerable of arithmeticke: meaſurable (as I may ſay) are the ſubiects of geometry.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of the ſubiect out of ſome O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the ſame ſubiect (<hi>Cicero</hi> (ſecond <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra</hi>) diſputeth that there was no contention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people of Campania, becauſe there was no honour. They are not carried (ſaith he) with the deſire of glory: becauſe where there is no publike honour, there the deſire of glory cannot be. There is no diſcord, neither by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention nor ambition: for there is nothing for which they ſhould ſtrive, nothing for which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150998:18"/>they ſhould warre, nothing for which they ſhould contend.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Propertius uſeth this argument.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of windes the Saylors talke, the Husbandmen of Bulls</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Soldiers of their wounds, and ſhepheards of their woolls</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 11. <hi>The Adiunct.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Adiunct?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Adiunct is that to which any thing is ſubiected: which argument though it be ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the ſubiect, yet more copious and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent: therefore of its ſignes <hi>Ovid</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: Rem: Anno.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some man (for ſuch there be) may count this ſmall</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet that helpes ſome which doth not profit all.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Make this playner?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe things which are called good and evill of the minde, body, and the whole man, are the adiuncts of the minde, body, man: alſo whatſoever happeneth without the ſubiect is the Adiunct.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not time alſo be reduced unto this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, as place was in the ſubiect, ſo is time in the Adiunct, <hi>viz.</hi> the induring of things paſt, preſent, to come.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What further is compriſed under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All thoſe quallities beſide the cauſes, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to the ſubiect, whether they be propet or common.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150998:19"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What it Proper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That which agreeth onely and wholly with the ſubiect, as laughing with a man, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a horſe, barking with a dogg.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is common?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That which is not proper after this manner.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of the Adiunct out of ſome Orator.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this kind of argument, <hi>Cicero</hi> in the defence of <hi>Roſcius</hi> the Comedian, cavelleth with <hi>Fanius Chereus.</hi> Doth not his head and eye-brewes, altogether bald, ſeeme to favour of malice, and cry out of deceit, doth he not ſeem to be compounded from the foote to the head, (if a man may coniecture by his ſhape) of frauds fallacies, lyes? Who therefore is altogether bald on the head and eyebrewes, leaſt he ſhould be ſaid to have one haire of a good man.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So <hi>Martiall</hi> lib. 2. mocketh <hi>Zoylus.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Red haire, black mouth, ſhort feet and ilke ſquint eyes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis marvell</hi> Zoylus <hi>if goodnes in thee lies.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>What further may be reduced under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Garments and company are Adiuncts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this kind of circumſtance, <hi>Dido</hi> going a hunting is magnificently ſet forth, <hi>Aeneid:</hi> 4.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The morne appeard,</hi> Dido <hi>forſooke the ſea,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The day ſtir up, toth heaven youth guides the way</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:150998:19"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Both nets &amp; gins with picke ſtanes all were reddy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Meſſalian horſe with hunting dogs ſo greedy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Princes did waite, the ſlow queene did expect.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With faire clad horſe, her way for to direct,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Forth commeth ſhee at length with mighty traine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In her long robe with many a long ſeame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Her horſe down trapt, with gold her hair was treſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Her robes with golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> books, together did ſhe wreſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the benefit of Adiuncts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is great uſe of Adiuncts to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects by which they are occupied.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this argument <hi>Plato</hi> foretold thoſe cities to be miſerable, where the multitude of Phyſitians and Iudges were wanting: becauſe, of neceſſity, there was converſant in thoſe ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, both intemperance, and iniuſtice.</p>
               <p>And thus much for the place of agreeings, from whence every agreeing argument may be ſaid to be one or the ſame: and all manner of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and (as I may ſay) identity are referred hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as the firſt and ſimple fountaines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 12. <hi>Diverſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>You have expounded the firſt agreeing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: the diſagreeing followeth, what then is diſagreeing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That which diſagreeth from the thing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are diſagreeings manifeſted?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150998:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſagreeings are equally manifeſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, and equally argued one of another, although they doe more clearely ſhine in their Diſagreeings.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of diſagreeings?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two, Diverſe and Oppoſite.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are Diverſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diverſes are diſagreeings which diſagree onely in reaſon.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the moſt frequent notes of ſpeech for this Argument?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe. Not this, but that; although, yet.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example from ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro Pempeio.</hi> He carried not the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but the enſignes of the victory.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give ſome other examples?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ovid ſecund: Art: Amand:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vliſſes</hi> was nos faire but Eloquent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aeneid:</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Triamus</hi> though held in duſt of death Yetſeaſed not.</p>
               <p>Alſo this of the like matter, <hi>Pro Lig:</hi> calleſt thou that wicked (ô <hi>Tub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro</hi>) why, he hath not hitherto deſerved this name. For ſome called error, ſome feare, that which more hardly, hope, deſire, hatred, pertinacy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the moſt grave temerity, none wicked beſides thy ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 13. <hi>Deſperates</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150998:20"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are Oppoſites?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Oppoſites are diſagreeings, which diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in reaſon and thing; therefore cannot bee attributed to the ſame, according to the ſame, to the ſame, and at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Make this plaine by example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So <hi>Socrates</hi> cannot be blacke and white of one and the ſame part. Father and ſonne of the ſame man; whole and ſick at the ſame time; but he may be white on the one part, blacke on another; Father of this, ſonne of that man; ſound to day, ſick to morrow.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>It ſhould ſeeme by this, that the one being affirmed the other is denied?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So it is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of Oppoſites?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſparates or contraries.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are Disparates?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſparates are oppoſites whereof one is oppoſed equally to many.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Greene, Aſhcolor, Red, are meanes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene white and black, which are Diſparates, both with the extreames &amp; among themſelves. So liberality and covetouſneſſe are diſparates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves. So a man a tree, a ſtone and infinite of this kinde are Diſparates; neither can one thing be, a man, a tree, a ſtone.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Virgill: Aeneid:</hi> 1. diſputeth by this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150998:21"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O virgin how ſhall I remember thee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſe countenance not mortall ſeemes to bee:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy voice is ſure aboue the humane reach</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Both which thee Goddes proves and ſo doe teach.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 14. <hi>Relates.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are contraries?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Contraries are Oppoſites whereof one is oppoſed to one only.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>What are the kindes of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are either affirming or denying.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is affirming?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Affirming is that of which both of them affirme.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many kindes hath it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two, Relates and Adverſes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are Relates?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Relates are Contraries, affirming of which one conſiſteth of the mutuall affection of the other: and from hence they are named Relates.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Make this plaine by example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Father, who hath a ſonne, and the ſonne who hath a Father, are relates.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>They may ſeeme by this to bee together by nature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So they are, ſo that he which perfectly knoweth the one, knoweth alſo the reſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give ſome examples of Relates?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150998:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro Marc.</hi> By which thou truely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeſt how much praiſe there is for the benefit given, when as for the receiving, is ſo much glory, <hi>Marc:</hi> againſt <hi>Soſib.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Soſibian, thou yeeld'ſt thou waſt borne thrall When flattering thou thy Father Lord doſt call.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Quint.</hi> lib. 5. cap. 10. If it be honeſt to place himſelfe at Rhoades, and to lodge at Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maereon. After which manner <hi>Tullius,</hi> in the perfect oration. It is therfore dangerous (ſaith he) leaſt any ſhould thinke it diſhoneſtie, to teach that in the great and glorious Art to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which it was honeſtie for him to learne.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Doth not earneſt affection ſometimes flow from theſe Relates?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cicero</hi> in his oration hath brought forth a certaine earneſt affection from theſe Relates. Now theſe are grave (ſaith he) wife of the Sonne in law, ſtep-mother of the Sonne, and baude of the daughter.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All this <hi>Ovid</hi> hath affected manifeſtly in his deſcription of the Iron age, <hi>Met.</hi> 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ne doth the gueſt ſafe in his Inne remaine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His hoſt him troubles who doth him retaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Siſters ene from their brethren are not free</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The husband longs the death of's wife to ſee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>She hateth him and gainſt him doth conſpire</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Curſed ſtepdam's alwayes in an ire.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150998:22"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Sonne before his time doth's fathers yeares in quire</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>But the argument of ſuch relations hath nothing contrary: yea it rather argueth mutuall cauſes: as, thou art my Father, I therefore am thy ſonne, how then appeareth the Contraries?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When I ſay I am thy father, I am not therefore thy Son, then are the contraries true.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 15. <hi>Adverſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are adverſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Adverſes are Contraries affirming, which are perpetually adverſe among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Aneid: 11. <hi>No health in warre, we all deſire peace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give further example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> White and blacke, hot and cold, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and vice, are oppoſed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Parad.</hi> 1. <hi>Cont. Epe.</hi> Yet they doe hold ſtrongly and defend accurately, that pleaſure is the cheife good: which to me truely doth ſeeme to be the voyce of beaſts, not of men; when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as whether God, or nature (as I may ſay) the mother of all things hath given thee a ſoule, then which nothing is more excellent, nothing more divine; doſt thou ſo caſt, and throw down thy ſelfe, as that thou thinkeſt there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150998:22"/>betwixt thee and the foure footed beaſts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherein conſiſts the force of this example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cicero</hi> hath oppoſed beaſts and men, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes: pleaſure is the good of beaſts, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of men.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So liberty and ſervitude in <hi>Tib. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>So ſervitude I ſee prepared for me, Yet parents freedome would farre better be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of an Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro Marcell.</hi> For temerity is never ioyned with wiſdome, neither is chance admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to councell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 16. <hi>Contradicents</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Having ſpoken of contraries affirming, we are come to contraries denying, what are they then?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Contraries denying are ſuch, of which one ſaith, the other denieth the ſame.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are Contradicents or Privants.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are Contradicents?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Contradicents are Contraries denying, of which one denyeth every where.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Iuſt; not iuſt, a creature, not acreature; it is, it is not: Theſe are Contradicents.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:150998:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro Murena.</hi> The ſentences of <hi>Cato</hi> &amp; <hi>Cicero</hi> are Contraries; this of the Stoicks, that man of the Academicks. The Dialogue is in theſe wordes. Thou haſt knowne nothing, yea ſomething, but not all things. Thou haſt done nothing meerly for thanks, yet refuſe not thanks when as thine office and truſt requireth it. Be not moved with mercy in condemning. But yet there is ſome prayſe of humanitie. Stand in thine owne opinion: except a better ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example from ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Mart. lib.</hi> 2.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Th'art faire</hi> Fabulla, <hi>rich, and al's a maid,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Can you deny, tis truth that I have ſaid?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But if thou boaſteſt of thy ſelfe too much,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Th'art neither faire, a virgine, nor yet rich.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>give another example out of ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cicero primo Tuſc.</hi> Forceth <hi>Atticus</hi> the Epicure by this argument to confeſſe, that the dead were not miſerable, if they were not at all; as the Epicures believe, I had rather (ſaith hee) thou ſhouldeſt feare <hi>Cerberus,</hi> then ſpeak ſo inconſiderately. <hi>Atticus,</hi> why? <hi>Marcus,</hi> that that which thou denieſt that thou ſaieſt. Where is thy wit? For when as thou ſayeſt he is miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, thou then ſayeſt, he is, which is not. Then after long diſputation <hi>Atticus</hi> ſaid, go to, now I grant that thoſe which are dead are not miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: becauſe thou haſt forced me to confeſſe, that they be not all, leſt they ſhould be miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:150998:23"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Terrence</hi> in <hi>Ev. Phedria</hi> frameth his ſpeech to <hi>Dorus,</hi> when as he had affirmed that which he denyed afterwards. After a manner (ſaith he) he ſaith, after a manner he denyeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 17. <hi>Privants.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are Privants?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Privants are contraries denying, of which one denieth in the ſame ſubiect onely, in which the affirmatiue (of its owne nature) is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the affirmative called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Habit.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what the negative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Privation.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Make this playner?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Motion and reſt, drunkenneſſe and ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, are compriſed under this head.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Mart. lib.</hi> 3.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Th'art drunken ſure, ſober thou would'ſt not do't,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may further be under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be blind, and to ſee.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro Celio.</hi> There is therefore one of this family, and he truely is greatly blinde: for hee ſhall take no griefe who ſhall not ſee her.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may further be under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Povertie and riches are thus oppoſed.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:150998:24"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Mart. lib. 5.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Poore ſhalt thou be</hi> Emilian <hi>if poore:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wealths never given but to the rich before.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>What further?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Death and life.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cont. Mil.</hi> Sit yee ſtill O revengers of this mans death; whoſe life if you thought you could reſtore, would you?</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What further?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Silence and Speech.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Primo Cat.</hi> What expecteſt thou the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the ſpeaker, whoſe ſilence thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeſt to be their pleaſures?</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What more?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Mortality and Immortality.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro Maro.</hi> I grieue when as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth ought to be immortall, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of one mortall life.</p>
               <p>And this ſufficeth to be ſpoken of Diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, from whence every thing may differ from another by certaine meanes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 18. <hi>Equalls.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Simple arguments were agreeings &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeings; we are now come unto Comparatives;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150998:24"/>what are Comparatives therefore?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Comparatives are thoſe which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared amongſt themſelves.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are they manifeſted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Although they bee equally knowne by the nature of compariſon, yet one to another is more knowne and illuſtrated then another: and oftentimes are iudged by ſhorter notes, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times diſtinguiſhed by fuller patts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may theſe parts be cald?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are named the Propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Reditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not comparatives alſo argue fictions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, Comparatives doe argue feigned things, and goe cauſe truſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the kindes of Compariſons?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Compariſon, is in Quantity, or Quality.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Quantity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Quantity is that whereby is ſhewed how much the thing compared is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the kindes of Quantity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Equalls or unequalls.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are Equalls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Equalls are thoſe of which there is one quantity.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Equall argument then?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An equall argument is, when an Equall is explicated by an Equall.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the notes of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Euen, equal, like, the ſame, that, ſo much the more, how much the more, by ſo much, by how much, ſo much, how much, not more not leſſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:150998:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Aeneid.</hi> 2. Equall with light windes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aeneid.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And mow't ſhould grow in equall age with thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aeneid</hi> 6.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Behold this thing Great Rome with earth is even</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The ſpirit of man ſhall alſo equall heaven.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>What further is neceſſary to theſe equalls?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A propoſition or Reddition doth diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Quart: Cat:</hi> Whoſe things done, and the vertues to the ſame, by which things one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the courſe is contained in its regions and bounds.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Aeneid. 4.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As well a bruiter of things falſe that be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As meſſenger of truth and verity.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <signed>Cat.</signed>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By how much I am worſt of poets all,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By ſo much thee men beſt of patrons call.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Ovid de Triſt. 4.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As many ſhells on ſhore, as roſes ſweete.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As many ſleeps as men, by popy ſeedes doe get.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As many beaſts in woods, fiſh in the ſea doe lie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As many birds as in the ayrie heavens doe fly,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So many griefs me paſſe, their number ſhould I tell</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Icarian waters I muſt ſurely number well.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Proceed to further examples?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Phil.</hi> 9. Neither had he more skill of the law then of iuſtice: therefore thoſe things
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150998:25"/>which the lawes had brought forth, chiefely the civill, he alwayes referred to eaſe and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: neither had hee rather approve actions of ſtrife, then take away controverſies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ovid de Art. Amand: 'Tis no leſſe vertue for to keepe then get.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro Mur.</hi> I acknowledge this to be equall for <hi>Lucius Murena:</hi> and ſo equall, that neither hee ſhall bee overcome by dignity, neither by dignity ſhall overcome thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. Whoſe burthen being common, why not a common pray of them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ter in Adelph.</hi> When as I care not for thine, care not thou for mine.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may further be compriſed under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of this place are thoſe that follow de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived truely from contraries, but treated of in the place of equals; as this of <hi>Mart. Soſibian thou yeeld'ſt, thou waſt borne thrall, When flattering thou thy father lord doſt call.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ovid</hi> 1. <hi>Faſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ther's price in price, the Cenſors honors give;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He giveth friendſhip, poore alone doe live.</hi>
               </l>
               <p>Q. <hi>But are they not more frequent from ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cicero Syl.</hi> Neither doe I underſtand my ſelfe to have beene angry. But if I defend him whom thou accuſeſt, why ſhould I not be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150998:26"/>angry with thee, who accuſeſt him whom I defend? hee ſaith I accuſe mine owne enemy; and I ſaid, I defend my friend. So <hi>primo Tuſc:</hi> But when as they confeſſe that there is force e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in vices to cauſe a miſerable life, why ſhould it not bee granted that there is force e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in vertues to effect a bleſſed life.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>It ſhould ſeeme by this, that contraries are ſequences of contraries?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So they are.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may further be compriſed under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sometimes there is put forth like for like.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such is the contention of the ſhepheards in <hi>Virg: Aeglog:</hi> 3. <hi>Damaetas</hi> firſt of all putting forth this riddle.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tell in what place and I will herry thee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For great</hi> Apollo's <hi>ſelfe, the welken large</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iuſt three els broad and no more ſeemes to bee:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And</hi> Menalcas <hi>anſwering in this other riddle.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tell in what place the flowers have their marge,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With kings names in their leaves inſcribed plain;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And to thy ſelfe take</hi> Phillis <hi>for thy paine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of feigned equalls?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Feigned equalls are ſuch as is in <hi>Aeſchinus Sacraticus</hi> wherein <hi>Socrates</hi> ſheweth <hi>Aſpatia</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Zenophons</hi> wife, &amp; <hi>Zenophon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Tell me I pray thee thou wife of <hi>Zeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon,</hi> if thy neighbour ſhould have better gold then thou, whether hadſt thou rather have hers
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150998:26"/>or thine? hers, ſaid ſhee. And if ſhee have a goune, and other womens garments of a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter price then thou, whether hadſt thou rather have hers or thine? hers, ſaid ſhe. Goe to then if ſhe have a better husband then thou, had'ſt thou rather have hers? here the woman blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. But <hi>Aſpatia</hi> ſpake to <hi>Zenophon</hi> himſelfe, I pray thee (ſaid ſhee) if thy neighbour have a better horſe then thou, had'ſt thou not rather have his or thine? His, ſaid he: but if he have better ground then thou, whether had'ſt thou rather have his? His, ſaid hee: <hi>viz.</hi> the beſt. But if hee have a better wife then thou haſt, whether had'ſt thou rather have his or thine? And here <hi>Zenophon</hi> alſo himſelfe held his peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 18. <hi>Greaters</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are unequalls?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Vnequals are thoſe of which the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity is not one.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the kindes of unequals?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Vnequall is greater or leſſer.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is greater?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Greater is that which quantity excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the proper notes of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not only, but alſo, I had rather this, then that, more alſo by grammaticall compariſon.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:150998:27"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cicero pro Mur.</hi> There is taken from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us not onely that verball counterfeit of prudence, but alſo that Lady of things Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it ſelfe: The thing is carried by force, not onely the hatefull Orator in pleading, or the pratler, but alſo the truely good is deſpiſed. A horrid ſouldier is loved.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not a certaine logicall gradation, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ioyned with a rethoricall climax taken from hence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro. Mil.</hi> Neither did he ſo handle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the people onely, but alſo to the Senate, neither to the Senate only, but alſo to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique preſident and ſouldiers: neither to theſe alone, but alſo to the power of thoſe, to whom the care of Senate ſouldiers, &amp; the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of <hi>Italy</hi> was committed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give a poeticall example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Iu. Sat.</hi> 8. Againſt a proud noble man, <hi>Rather had I</hi> Thirſes <hi>thy Sire ſhould bee, Whil'ſt that</hi> Aeacides <hi>is like to thee: And that thou ſhouldſt with</hi> Vulcan <hi>armor make, Then for</hi> Achilles <hi>ſonne men ſhould thee take. Or that thy feature ſhould like</hi> Thirſes <hi>be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Proceede to further example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro. Marc.</hi> Having more admiration then glory, <hi>Aeneid.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O fellowes we theſe evills knew before,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150998:27"/>God will them end, we greater far have bore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cic. pro Mur.</hi> Be not ſo uniuſt, that when as thy fountaines are opened by thine enemies, our rivers ſhould bee ſtopped up even by our friends.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of a gradation, without a rethoricall climax?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ter. Thr.</hi> But doth <hi>Thais</hi> give me many thankes for it? <hi>Gn.</hi> Many. <hi>Thr.</hi> ſayeſt thou ſo? is ſhe glad? <hi>Gn.</hi> Not ſo much for the gift it ſelfe, as that it was given by thee; for that ſhee triumpheth in good earneſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are not alſo greaters feigned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, and of great force.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ter. Hert.</hi> A noble man if hee be made a lover can never undergoe the charges, much leſſe thou then. <hi>Aeneid.</hi> 5.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O great</hi> Aeneas <hi>although</hi> love <hi>ſhould not</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Promiſe to helpe or aide me now one iot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I hope that</hi> Italy <hi>ſhall reach to heaven,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The windes once chang'd their forces croſſe have driven.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ariſeing from black night i'th city caſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our power is weake, our greateſt ſtrength but waſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 20. <hi>Leſſers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Leſſer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Leſſer is that whoſe quantity is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:150998:28"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is a Leſſer iudged?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Oftentimes by proper notes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be theſe notes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not onely, but not at all: rather this then that, when as, as alſo.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By grammatical, compariſon.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How laſtly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the denying of partes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of the notes out of ſome O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cic. ſecund. Cat.</hi> No man not onely of <hi>Rome,</hi> but in no corner of all <hi>Italy</hi> was ever op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with ſo great a taxe, as that hee once knew of ſo incredible a <hi>Ceſar. Cat.</hi> 1. Thou canſt rather as an Exul tempt, then as a Conſul vexe the common wealth. <hi>Ag.</hi> 2. Which when to all it is very hard and an evill reaſon, then truely to me above the reſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give poeticall examples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ovid Triſt.</hi> 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>More fierce then</hi> Buſiros, <hi>more fierce then he,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who in flow fire his Oxe burnt furiouſly.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ovid. pri. de rem. amor.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy body to redeeme beare ſword and fire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ne drinke to coole thy thirſly hot deſire:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſave thy ſoule wilt thou not all forbeare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This part exceedes the other price by farre.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of thoſe which are done by the denying of parts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Phil.</hi> 9. All in all ages who have had the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150998:28"/>underſtanding of the law in this city, if they might bee brought together into one place are not to be equalled with <hi>Servius Sulpitius: Cat.</hi> 2. Although thoſe which ſay that <hi>Catilina</hi> is gone to <hi>Meſſilia,</hi> doe not ſo much complaine of it, as feare it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is it not ſometimes without notes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro Mur:</hi> Thou art ſo much wanting from the perfection of great workes, as the foundation, which thou thinkeſt thou haſt not yet layd. <hi>Pro Arch:</hi> The ſtones and deſartes often times anſwer to the voyce; wilde beaſts are tamed and ſubdued by ſinging: ſhall not then the inſtructions of the Poets in the beſt thing move us?</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there not alſo a gradation from leſſers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ver:</hi> 7. Is it a great act to overthrow the city <hi>Rome,</hi> to beate a knave, to kill a Parriſide, what ſhall I ſay? to hang him upon the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are not leſſers alſo ſometimes feigned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Virg: Aeglog:</hi> 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The light held hynds in th'aire ſhall feed therfore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And in the Ocean all the fiſhes die:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For want of water on the naked ſhore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:150998:29"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The wandring</hi> Parthyan <hi>firſt ſhall drinken dry tide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Huge</hi> Araxis, <hi>and guſling</hi> Germany:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sucke downe their thirſty throates, ſwift</hi> Tigris</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ere his deare lovely face ſhall from my boſome ſlide.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Phil.</hi> 2. O filthy thing? not onely in the ſight but alſo to heare of? if it had happened to thee amongſt thine inhumane pots, who would not have accounted it filthy? but in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the <hi>Romans</hi> about publique affaires<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the maſter of the horſe to whom it is not comely to belch, hee vomiting a cruſt of bread and wine, filled his lap and all the tribunall with ſtinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 21. <hi>Likes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>You have expounded compariſon in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, compariſon in quality followeth, what there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is quality?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Quality is that whereby the things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared are ſaid to be ſuch.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of quality?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Like or diſlike?</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are likes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Likes are thoſe of which there is the ſame quality.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are likes called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Like is called proportion, as the likes are proportionable.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:150998:29"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the notes of likenes, whereby it is concluded in one word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Like, effigies, in that manner as alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials of diſlikenes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be they?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as this not otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of the firſt ſort?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Aeneid:</hi> 1. His mouth and ſhoulders be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like to God. <hi>Phil:</hi> 9. Although <hi>Servius Suſpicius</hi> could leave no clearer monument then his ſonne, the effigies of his manners, vertues, conſtancy, piety, wit.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ovid. Triſt.</hi> 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For he or none, even he that made the wound,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Onely</hi> Achilles <hi>'tis can make me ſound.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Proceed to farther examples?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. In Phiſ.</hi> There was one day which was to mee the likeneſſe of immortality, wherein I returned to my countrey. <hi>Ver:</hi> 1. But preſently from the ſame likenes of a man as it were by ſome <hi>Circean</hi> pot, hee is made a Beare. <hi>Pro Pomp.</hi> Therefore all in this place doe behold <hi>Conſ. Pompeius</hi> not as one ſent from the citty, but fallen from heaven. Aeneid. 3. They doe not that which I have commanded. <hi>Ter:</hi> I am not, neither have beene otherwiſe then he.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the partition of likenes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Disjoyned or continued.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a disjoyned ſimilitude?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A disjoyned ſimilitude is when as foure
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150998:30"/>termes are diſtinguiſhed to the thing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Eglog:</hi> 5.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So me thy ſong as ſleepe on graſſe doth queme</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The travailer, his weary lims to drench.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the force of this example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſongs to the hearers, as ſleepe to the weary, are foure diſtinct termes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ad fratrem:</hi> As the beſt governours can not overcome the force of the tempeſt, ſo the wiſeſt men often times cannot overcome the violence of fortune.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew the force of this example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Here are foure termes, as the governour to the ſhippe, ſo wiſe men to fortune.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Proceed to farther examples?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Triſt.</hi> 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the yellow gold in flaming fire is ſeen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So men may truſt, behold, in time that's ſharp and keen</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cic. Phil.</hi> 2. But even as thoſe who in a great ſickenes doe not taſte the ſweetneſſe of meate, ſo the luſtfull, covetous, wicked have not the taſte of true praiſe. <hi>Virg.</hi> made theſe verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All night it rain'd, next day the ſignes are ſeene,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Th' Empires parted</hi> Ceſar <hi>and</hi> love <hi>betweene.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Battillus</hi> arrogated them to himſelfe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a great reward: therefore <hi>Virgill</hi> in theſe verſes mocketh <hi>Battillus.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I made theſe rimes, another had the land,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:150998:30"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So birds you neaſts not for your ſelves have made,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So you ô Bees make hony not for you:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So you ô Sheepe beare wooll but not for you,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So you ô Oxen plough but not for you.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are not the notes ſometimes omitted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, ſometimeſ there is no note at all.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Virg: Eglog:</hi> 2.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ah my faire boy truſt not thy hew too much,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hurtles though blacke, by every handſome hand</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Are pluck'd, while dayſes none vouchſafe to touch,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All be they white, yet ſhed they as they ſtand.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is continuall likeneſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A continuall likenes is when as the firſt terme is to the ſecond, ſo the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the third.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. De Leg:</hi> 3. See you not that this is the Magiſtrates power that he ſhould rule and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe right, profitable, and agreeing things with the lawes: for as the lawes doe governe the Magiſtrates, ſo the Magiſtrates doe rule the people.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the force of this example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Here are three termes, Lawes, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, People.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Have not feigned likeneſſes equall force with theſe above?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It appeareth chiefly in this explicated ſimilitude of <hi>Eſope</hi> his Apology taken out of</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:150998:31"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Horace Epiſt.</hi> 1.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But if</hi> Romes <hi>people aske me happily.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Why not 'mongſt Iudges on the bench ſit I:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And doe that which they love, fly that they hate?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I anſwer as the crafty Fox of late.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When tooth-ſick lion he this meſſage ſent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faine would I come to that thing was I bent:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But that I ſaw the ſteps of many feet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That way to goe, none back againe to get.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 22. <hi>Diſlikes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are diſlikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſlikes are comparatives, whoſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is diverſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the proper notes of diſlikes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſlike, different, another.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro Plan.</hi> Although the paying of mony and thankes bee unlike. <hi>Aeneid.</hi> 1. O ancient houſe? O how unlike for that Lord to governe <hi>Caeſ. Pri. Bel. Gal.</hi> All theſe differed in their tongues, inſtructions, lawes. <hi>Agra.</hi> 2. One is knowne by his countenance, another by his voyce, another by his gate. <hi>De Nat. Deo.</hi> 2. Becauſe I have begun to doe otherwiſe then I had ſaid in the begining.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Are not diſlikes alſo knowne by denying ſhe likes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:150998:31"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. De Orat:</hi> 2. Philoſophy is not like the other artes: <hi>Aeneid:</hi> 2. But he was not of that ſeede wherein thou remembreſt <hi>Achilles,</hi> ſuch was <hi>Priamus</hi> his enemy. <hi>Lor. Epiſt.</hi> 2. There is not the ſame age, the ſame minde, <hi>ad frat.</hi> 1. So thy ring is not as a certaine veſſell, but as thy ſelfe: <hi>Phil:</hi> 3. This certaine day he is wont to expect not ſo much of ſacrifice as counſell.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give ſome poeticall examples?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this argument the ſhepheard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth his error. <hi>Aeglog:</hi> 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ah fond friend</hi> Melibe <hi>I whilom dempt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That famous city which I now and then,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In common chat amongſt our countrey men:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Have heard yea cliped by the name of</hi> Rome,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Certes for all the world cib to our homely home: and by and by,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>— <hi>ſo did I dare.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Kids liken to their Goates, whelps to their dams,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And moule hills wont to mountaines to compare.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew the force of this example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As neither the whelpes to the dogges, nor kids to their dams, ſo neither is <hi>Mantua</hi> like to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Be not notes of diſlikes ſometimes wanting?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, often times, and the diſlikeneſſe is more clearely explicated.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example out of ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Quint. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>Brutus</hi> ſlew the children of the traytors: <hi>Muntius</hi> did puniſh by death
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150998:32"/>the vertue of his ſonne.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cat:</hi> the ſunne ſets and riſeth againe: but when our little light ſetteth, there is a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall night.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 23. <hi>Conjugates.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Hitherto you have expounded the firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, thoſe derived from the firſt follow, what are they then?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe derived from the firſt are theſe, which are even to that which they argue, as the firſt from whence they are derived.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the kindes of theſe arguments?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A conjugate, a notation, a diſtribution, and a definition.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are conjugates?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Conjugates are names drawne diverſly from the ſame principle.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Iuſtice, juſt, juſtly.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there not a ſymboll in conjugates of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing arguments?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Propert: lib:</hi> 2.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Becauſe in love there is no liberty,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who ever loves that man can ne'r be free.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew the force of this example?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:150998:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Here liberty is the cauſe why we ſhould be free.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cic: Nat: Deo:</hi> 2. Where he ſpeaketh of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant. He commanded that the tables of ſilver in which were the images of the gods, ſhould be taken away, in which after the manner of the <hi>Grecians</hi> ſhould be ingraven. The goods of the gods, ſaying, that he was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to uſe of their goodnes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew the force of this example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Gods are good, therefore their goodnes is to bee uſed: here from the effects it is directed to the cauſes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ter:</hi> I am a man, no humane thing is ſtrange to me.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is it not ſometimes from the ſubject to the adjunct?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Phil:</hi> 2. I will not handle thee as a Conſul, leaſt thou handle mee as one ſtanding for the conſulſhip. <hi>In Piſ:</hi> When as all the cauſe was of the Conſuls and Senate, both the Conſuls &amp; Senate had need of my helpe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 24. <hi>Notations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is notation?</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:150998:33"/>
               <p>A. <hi>Notation is the interpretation of a name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are names?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Names truely are notes of things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> May there not be rendred a reaſon of the names?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Yes, either from the derivation or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, if they be made by true notation, from ſome firſt argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give example?</p>
               <p>A. Homo ab humo. Ovid: Fast: <hi>6.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Stat vi terra ſua, vi ſtando veſta vocatur.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Shew the force of this example?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>This is a notation from the cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give another example?</p>
               <p>A. At focus a flammis, &amp; quod fovit omnia dictus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Shew the force of this example?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>This is a notation from the effects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give another example?</p>
               <p>A. Vir: <hi>4.</hi> O Verrea praeclara! quid enim ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiſti, quo non attuleris tecum iſtum diem? &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim quam tu domum, quam urbem adijſti, quod fanum denique, quod non everſum atque exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum reliqueris? quare appellentur ſanè iſta Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea quae non ex nomine, ſed ex moribus, natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que tua conſtituta eſſe videantur.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Shew the force of this example?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>This is alſo a notation from the effects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give another example?</p>
               <p>A. Ovid: Faſt: <hi>1.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prima dies tibi carua datur, dea cardinis haec eſt.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:150998:33"/>
               <p>Nomine clauſa aperit, claudit aperta ſuo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Wherein is the force of this example?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>This is a notation from the ſubjects in the inward, about which the deity of this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe is exerciſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give another example?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>From the adjuncts, there is a notation from</hi> Bambalion. Phil. <hi>2.</hi> Quia balbus &amp; ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidus: hinc igitur cavilatio in Antonium generum. Tuae conjugis, bonae faeminae, locupletat is quidem certè, Bambalio quidem pater, homo nullo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, nihil illo contemptius, qui propter haeſitantiam linquae ſtuporemque cordis cognomen ex contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia traxerit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Shew the force of this example?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>This is a notation from adjuncts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Are there not notations alſo from diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Yes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give example.</p>
               <p>A. Quint. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> Lucus, quia umbra apacus, parum luceat: &amp; ludus quia ſit longiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè a luſu, &amp; dis quia minimè dives.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> May not notation bee alſo from compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Yes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give example?</p>
               <p>A. Pyropus, quod ignis flammam imitotur.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But is there not, as to the notation to his name, ſo an affection of the name to the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:150998:34"/>
               <p>A. <hi>Yes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give example?</p>
               <p>A. Animi plenus, ergo animoſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Shew the contrary?</p>
               <p>A. Animoſus, ergo animi plenus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 25. <hi>Diſtribution.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the other derived arguments?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſtribution and definition.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there not a reciprocall affection in both theſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the affection in the diſtribution?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of all parts with the whole.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the affection in the definition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the definition with the things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a diſtribution?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A diſtribution is, when the whole is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed into parts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the whole?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The whole is that which containeth parts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are parts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Partes are thoſe which are contained of the whole.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>It ſhould ſeeme then that the diſtinction of the whole into parts is diſtribution?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So I ſaid.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150998:34"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is then the collection of the parts to the making up of the whole?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is called induction.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whence is diſtribution taken?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſtribution is taken from arguments altogether agreeing, but diſagreeing amongſt themſelves: therefore it ſhall bee by ſo much more accurate, by how much the agreeings of the partes ſhall be with the whole, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing among themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 26.</hi> The diſtribution from the cauſe.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whence is the firſt diſtribution?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The firſt diſtribution is from abſolute agreeings.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are theſe abſolute agreeings?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The cauſes and effects.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is diſtribution from the cauſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſtribution from the cauſes, is when the partes are cauſes of the whole. Here the diſtribution of perfect into its members is greatly prayſed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is perfect?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Perfect is the whole, to which the parts are eſſentiall.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a member?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A member is a part of the whole.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Grammer is divided into Etymology,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150998:35"/>and Syntaxis; Rhetoricke, into Elocution and action; Dialectica, into invention and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for thoſe artes are conſtituted of thoſe partes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the principall diſtribution?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When the explication of a longer thing is received.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give examples?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Georg:</hi> 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What makes glad corne, &amp; how to till the ground,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How to plant elms that be ſo ſtrong and ſound:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How to guide oxen, cattell how to tend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And how the little pretty bee defend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I will declare.</hi> —</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cic: pro Mur:</hi> I underſtand O you Iudges, that the whole accuſation hath thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> parts, one of which is in reprehenſion of life, another in contention of dignity, the third touching the fault.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the ſecond kinde of handling this kinde of argument?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Either from the partes to the whole; or from the whole to the partes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cat:</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Quintia <hi>is faire to many, ſo to me,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I will not therefore this ſame thing deny;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But wholly faire I will not ſay ſhe's not:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>True beauty in her there is not a jot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lesbius <hi>faire in every part moſt fine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:150998:35"/>
                  <l>Venus <hi>adorn'd her, cleare did make her ſhine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 27.</hi> The distribution from the effects, alſo the genus and species.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the diſtribution from the effects?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The diſtribution from the effects, is when the partes are effects.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In a ſhippe the ſea-men, ſome ſcale the maſts, ſome runne in at the doores, ſome draw water, the governour holdeth the rudder in the ſhip.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not diſtribution of genus into ſpecies be compriſed under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, diſtribution of genus into ſpecies doth here excell.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is genus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Genus is the whole eſſentiall in parts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is ſpecies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Species is the parts of genus.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We ſay a living creature is the genus of a man, and a beaſt: for a living creature is the whole of that effect, <hi>viz.</hi> a corporall living ſubſtance, which commonly pertaineth to the beaſts and men: wee ſay the ſpecies of a man and a beaſt is living becauſe they are parts of a living ſubject, which living eſſence they have common: wee ſay a man the genus of every
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150998:36"/>man, and a lion the genus of every lion, but contrary, every man the ſpecies of a man, every lion of a lion.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the kindes of the genus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The genus is moſt generall or ſubalternat.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of the species?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſpecies is ſubalternate or moſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the moſt generall genus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The moſt generall genus is that of which there is no kindes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In logicall invention an argument is the moſt generall genus of artificialls and inartifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialls.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſubalternate genus, and the ſubalternate species?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſubalternate genus, as alſo the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alternate ſpecies, is that which is the ſpecies of this, but the genus of that.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The cauſe is the ſpecies of an abſolute arguing argument, but the genus of the matter and forme.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what is the moſt speciall ſpecies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The moſt ſpeciall ſpecies is that which is individable into other ſpecies.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The matter and forme ſingly.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the genus and species notes of?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the cauſes and effects.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:150998:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In a living thing there is a corporeall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence which in the matter is belonging com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to the ſpecies, as alſo the faculty of life and ſence, which in the forme pertaineth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to the ſpecies.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>It ſhould ſeeme that the genus containeth the cauſes, which doe attaine to the species of it; and therefore contrarily, the species containes the effects of their genus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So it is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>From whence then is that univerſall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſnes and excellency?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From hence, becauſe it declareth the cauſes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew ſome example now of the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the genus into ſpecies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſtribution of genus into ſpecies is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry excellent truly, but hard and ſeldome found, yet we will bring what illuſtrations and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples wee can. <hi>Ovid: Met:</hi> 1. Divideth living creatures into five ſpecies; ſtarres, birds, beaſts, fiſh, men: hee giveth life to the ſtarres as the Philoſophers doe.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No region is without ſome living thing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Starres in the skies the formes of gods being:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Birds in the aire in abundance be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beaſts on the earth, and fiſhes in the ſea.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But yet 'mongſt theſe a creature more divine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who may them rule and governe all in fine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There wanted much untill that man was borne.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>So <hi>Cic: Offic:</hi> 1. divideth vertue into foure
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150998:37"/>ſpecies, prudence, juſtice, fortitude, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance; but all that is honeſt ſpringeth out of one of theſe foure parts, for either it is conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in the knowledge and skill of the truth, or in the defending the ſociety of men, and giving every one his owne; alſo in truſt of things bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained, or in a high minde and admirable great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and courage, or laſtly in all things which are made and called order and meanes in which is modeſty and temperance,</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is diſtribution of the genus into the formes of the ſpecies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſtribution of the genus into the formes of the ſpecies is the ſame; becauſe the forme with the genus, conſtitute their ſpecies.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of living creatures, one is ſpeaking, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dumbe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not genus and species bee handled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and ſeverally?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, genus &amp; ſpecies are not only hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led after this ſimple forme of diviſion, but alſo apart one from another.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro Arc:</hi> But leaſt any ſhould wonder that we ſay ſo, that there is a certaine faculty of wit, and this reaſon or diſcipline of ſpeaking, neither that we have truely given our ſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to this ſtudy; for all artes which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to humanity, have a certaine common band, and are contained (as it were) in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150998:37"/>knowledge amongſt themſelves.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew the force of this example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Art is the genus, poeſie and eloquence the ſpecies.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the genus handled alſo by the spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ovid: de Triſt:</hi> 4.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fill thy ſad matter with thy vertues grave,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hot glory doth decay, it none can ſave:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who had knowne</hi> Hector <hi>if</hi> Troy <hi>well had beene?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Through publique vices way to vertue's ſeene.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thine art ô</hi> Typhis <hi>lyes, if in the ſea</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There be no floods, if men be well truly,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then Phoebus art decayeth inſtantly.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That which they hid, and is not knowne for good,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Appeares at laſt, and ſhewes where evill ſtood.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Q. <hi>But are there no ſpeciall examples fitted to this kinde?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, ſuch as this. <hi>Attic.</hi> 7. Wilt thou leave the city? what if the French men come? The common wealth hee ſaith is not in walls but altars and religion. <hi>Theomiſtocles</hi> did the ſame, and a whole hoſt of <hi>Barbarians</hi> were not able to take one city. But? <hi>Pericles</hi> did not ſo, who in the yeare almoſt before fifty, when he kept nothing but a wall; our city before be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken they kept the tower notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:150998:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 28.</hi> Diſtribution from the ſubject.</head>
               <l>Q. <hi>What is the other distribution?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The other diſtribution is of agreeings after a certaine manner.</l>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are agreeings after a certain manner?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> The ſubjects and adjuncts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the diſtribution from ſubjects?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The diſtribution from ſubjects is, when the parts are ſubjects.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cat:</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy maiden head's not wholly thine I wene,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One part thy father gave, the part betweene</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou of thy mother had'ſt, ſo that to thee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>None but the third remaineth for to be.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Therefore reſiſt not two, cast not away</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The thing thy parents gave to thee I ſay.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example out of ſome Orator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cic: Tuſc:</hi> 1. There are therefore three kindes of good, as I underſtand from the <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks,</hi> to whoſe uſe oftener then I am wont wee give place. There are therefore thoſe kindes of good, whilſt that the external things of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy are caſt upon the ground, &amp; becauſe they are to bee undertaken they are called good. There are other divine things which doe more near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerne us, and are heavenly, ſo that thoſe who have attained them, why may I not
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150998:38"/>call them after a manner bleſſed, yea moſt happy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 29.</hi> Diſtribution from adjuncts.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is diſtribution from adjuncts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Diſtribution from adjuncts is, when the parts are adjuncts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of men, ſome are ſound, ſome ſicke, ſome rich, ſome poore.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give a poeticall example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Virg: Georg:</hi> 1. Divideth the world into five partes, the middle ſcorching hot, the other two extreame cold, the two laſt temperate.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Five zones the heavens doe hold, the middle hot:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Sun there burnes, cold in it there is not,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But on the right and left hand there is ſeene.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Raine, froſt and cold, that's bitter, ſharpe &amp; keen.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The two laſt temperate, yet in them is</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mortality, and many ſickneſſes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an Orators example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Caeſ: Bel: Gal:</hi> 1. All <hi>France</hi> is divided into three parts; of which, one the <hi>Belgians</hi> inhabite, the other the <hi>Aequitans,</hi> the third thoſe who in their tongue are called <hi>Cetts,</hi> in our language the <hi>Gaules.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:150998:39"/>
               <head>CAP. 30. <hi>Definition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is definition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Definition is when it is explicated what the thing is, and that interchangeably may bee argued with the thing defined.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of definition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A definition is perfect or imperfect.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the perfect definition called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This is properly called a definition.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the imperfect called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A deſcription.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a perfect definition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A perfect definition is a definition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of the onely cauſes which conſtitute the eſſence: ſuch as the cauſes comprehended by the genus and forme.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> After this manner is a man defined, <hi>viz.</hi> by the genus, (a living creature) we underſtand (as it is ſaid) a corporeall eſſence full of life and ſenſe, which is the matter and a part of the forme of a man, to which (if thou addeſt reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable) thou comprehendeſt the whole forme of a man, by the whole faculty of his life, ſenſe, reaſon.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>It ſhould ſeeme then that the perfect defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition is nothing elſe then an univerſall ſymboll
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150998:39"/>of the cauſes, conſtituting the eſſence and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So it is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The artes have ſuch definitions, Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of well ſpeaking; Rethoricke of pleading well; Dialectica of diſputing well; Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke of numbring well; Geometry of meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 31. <hi>Deſcription.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is deſcription?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Deſcription is a definition defining the thing from other arguments alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give example?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>This is the deſcription of a man, a man is a living creature, mortall, capable of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Are not proper circumſtances alſo mingled with common cauſes ſometimes?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Yes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Then it ſeemeth that ſuccint brevity is not alwayes in this kinde?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>No, oftentimes it deſireth a clearer and greater explication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give an example out of ſome Orator?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. In Mil:</hi> Glory is deſcribed. But yet of all rewards of vertue (if there be a reaſon of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewardes) the greateſt is glory; this one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth us touching the ſhortneſſe of our life,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150998:40"/>cauſeth that wee are preſent with the abſent dead, maketh us to live to conclude, by theſe ſteppes wee doe ſeeme to aſcend into heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Give a poeticall example?</p>
               <p>A Aeneid: <hi>4. Fame is deſcribed.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>From <hi>Libeans</hi> temple cometh forth great fame,</l>
                  <l>Nought ſwifter then ill newes which beares this name,</l>
                  <l>Moving ſhe goes, by going ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth ſhe gets,</l>
                  <l>She feares at firſt, at laſt with windes ſhe fleets.</l>
                  <l>Walkes on the earth, her head ſhe lifts to'th skie,</l>
                  <l>Earth brought her forth, the Gods were angry;</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Caeus</hi> and <hi>Encelladus</hi> his land,</l>
                  <l>She was at laſt as I doe underſtand;</l>
                  <l>Her feet were ſwift, her wings moſt hurful were</l>
                  <l>A horrid monſter, wicked, full of feare,</l>
                  <l>As many feathers as upon her are:</l>
                  <l>So many eyes attend her every where.</l>
                  <l>So many tongues, ſo many mouthes doe ſound,</l>
                  <l>So many yeares doe leſſen her around.</l>
                  <l>In night ſhe flies through heaven, &amp; in the ſhade</l>
                  <l>About the earth ſhe goes, no noyſe is made:</l>
                  <l>She ſitteth by the light on houſes high,</l>
                  <l>And cauſeth townes to quiver fearefully;</l>
                  <l>As well a bruiter of things falſe that be,</l>
                  <l>As meſſengers of truth and verity.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Proceede to further example?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Such are the deſcriptions of plant? an living creatures, in phyſicke: alſo of rivers mountaines, cities, in geography and hiſtory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:150998:40"/>
               <head>CAP. 32. <hi>Divine teſtimony.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>You have expounded the artificial ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, the inartificiall followeth; tell me then what an inartificiall argument is?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An inartificiall argument is, that which argueth not by its owne nature, but taketh force from ſome artificiall argument.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>It ſeemeth by this when a hidden truth of things is more ſubtily ſearched for, that this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument hath ſmall force of proofe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So it is, but in civill and humane things oftentimes this argument effecteth the greateſt truſt, from the moving arguments, if wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, vertue, and good will be preſent.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In one name it is called teſtimony.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of teſtimony?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Divine or humane.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. What may be compriſed under the head of divine teſtimony?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not onely the miracles of the gods, but alſo the anſwers of prophets and fortune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellers, are counted amongſt divine teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All theſe are brought forth. <hi>Cat:</hi> 3. For that I may omit (ſaith the Orator) the fires ſeene in the night from the Weſt, and the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150998:41"/>of heaven, as alſo lightning, as earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, with other many things done to us Conſuls, as thoſe which are now done, doe ſeeme to proclaime the gods immortality. And a little after, at which time when the <hi>Araſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> were come together out of all <hi>Herturia,</hi> they ſaid that ſlaughter, burning, periſhing of the lawes, civill and domeſticall warre, and the fall of the whole city and empire approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unleſſe the immortall gods pleaſed by all reaſon, by their power ſhould change thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinies. At length when hee had ſaid that they mocked at the anſwer of the <hi>Ariſpatians,</hi> and that they did more regard the ſigne of <hi>Iove,</hi> turning to the Eaſt, he then ſaid; but is not hee ſo preſent that it ſhould ſeeme to be done at the becke of the mighty <hi>Iove,</hi> that when this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before my doore by my command and conjuration, the Iudges being then in the houſe of <hi>Concordia,</hi> at the ſame time there appeared a ſigne: which being turned towards you and the Senate, both you and the Senate ſaw mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly laid open, who they were that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the health of all men.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That of <hi>Tibullus</hi> is more ſhort.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But if that oracles true things doe tell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then this in our name ſee thou doe declare:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That he doth promiſe</hi> Delius <hi>to give,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To be thy ſpouſe with whom thou'lt happy live.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:150998:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 33.</hi> Teſtimony from humane law and ſentences.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What bee the kindes of humane teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Humane teſtimony is common or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is common?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Law; and a famous ſentence.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is legall teſtimony?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Legall teſtimony is both unwritten and written.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Bring forth authority for this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Pro Mil:</hi> For there is (O ye Iudges) a law not written, but borne with us; which we have not received, learned, read; but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, drawne, expreſſed from nature: as if our life ſhould bee in ſome hazard, force danger, either of theeves or enemies, all honeſt reaſon were to bee ſought of ſafety; but if the twelve tables will have the night theefe, yea the day theefe to, if he defend himſelfe after any manner killed without puniſhment; who is there that will thinke him that is ſlaine to bee puniſhed, when as there is a ſword reached to us, to kill that man by the lawes themſelves.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are famous ſentences?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Proverbes.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:150998:42"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They bee ſuch as theſe. <hi>Pares cum pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus facilimè congregantur. Spartam nactus es, hanc ex orna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may farther be under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sayings of wiſedome alſo.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Noſce teipſum. Nequid nimis. Sponde praeſto ad detrimentum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is proper teſtimony?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as this of <hi>Plato.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Quinti: frat:</hi> And then truely <hi>Plato</hi> the Prince of wiſdome and learning thought thoſe common wealthes bleſſed, if either learned and wiſe men gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, or thoſe that did governe, placed all their ſtudy in wiſedome and learning.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Proceed to further example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such were in the Poets <hi>Aeneid:</hi> 4. Learne juſtice and admonitions, and contemne not the rich. So in <hi>Homer.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ajax</hi> led out of <hi>Salaminus</hi> twelve ſhips.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Magatenſes</hi> were overcome by the <hi>Atho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are teſtimonies of the living?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Teſtimonies of the living, are not onely when it is inquired of ground, felling of wood and ſuch like buſineſſe, but alſo there are teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of obligation, confeſſing oath.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of obligation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Phil:</hi> 5. For I dare bind my faith, <hi>(P.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150998:42"/>C.)</hi> to you and the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> that truely when no force conſtrained me I durſt not doe; and I feared an opinion of timerity, in a thing greatly hurtfull; I promiſe and ſweare <hi>(P. C.)</hi> to become alwayes ſuch a citizen to <hi>Ceſar</hi> as he himſelfe is, and as wee ought chiefly to wiſh or deſire.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Have we not an obligation ſet forth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with a pledge?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes. <hi>Virg Eglog:</hi> 3.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wilt then by turnes, we hand to hand doe try,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What either can, and prove each by our deed;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ile paune this heifer, (which leaſt thou deny)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>She twiſe hath come already to the payle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And two twins ſuckles at this time now ſay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What paune thou'lt gage with her to countervail.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of confeſſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Confeſſion is free or extorted by tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is this latters properly called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A queſtion.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such an argument there is againſt <hi>Milon</hi> whom <hi>Cicero</hi> derided. Goe to then, what or how is the queſtion? How? where was <hi>Roſcius?</hi> where was <hi>Caſca?</hi> Doth <hi>Clodius</hi> lay ſnares for <hi>Milon?</hi> he hath done; ſurely the gallowes. He hath done nothing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What further may be reduced hitherto?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hitherto may bee referred the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which wee uſed when wee bring forth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150998:43"/>our approbation, and experience of our affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ver:</hi> 4. Even <hi>Volcatio</hi> if hee had come freely, would he have given a little booke? he ſhall come, he ſhall be tryed; no man truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth it. <hi>Ter:</hi> ſpend thy time in letters, in the woods, in muſicke: it is meete for youth to know theſe liberall thinges, I will give di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give a poeticall example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ovid. Triſt:</hi> 3.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The which that thou mayſt better credit me,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Try thou my paines, beleeve it then to be.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example alſo of the teſtimony of an oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Aeneid:</hi> 6.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I ſweare byth' gods, and all in earth unſeene;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I have departed from thy ſhore ô queene.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>This reciprocation ſeemeth to be more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, as becauſe the teſtimony is true, the witnes is alſo true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So it is: and thus much ſuffiſeth to have ſpoken of invention, the firſt part of the ſcience Dialectica.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:150998:43"/>
            <head>THE SECOND BOOKE OF <hi>PETER RAMVS</hi> HIS Dialectica of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 1.</hi> What Iudgement is.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>Hitherto the firſt part of Dialectica in Invention hath bin expounded, the other part fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, in Iudgement, what then is Iudgement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Iudgement is the ſecond part of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke of diſpoſing arguments to bee iudged well.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are they iudged?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Every thing is iudged by a certaine rule of diſpoſition.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>It may be thought then that this part of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke is called both judgement and diſpoſition from hence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So it is.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 2.</hi> An affirmative or negative Axioma.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of Iudgement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Iudgement is Axiomaticall, or Diano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:150998:44"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an Axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Axioma is the diſpoſition of an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, with an argument, wherein ſomewhat is iudged to bee, or not to be.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it called, and whence receiveth it the name?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the Lattin of <hi>Enuntiatum,</hi> it is called <hi>Enuntiation;</hi> of <hi>Pronuntiatum, Pronuntiation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the affections of an Axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Axioma is affirmative or negatiue.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is affirmative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Affirmative is when the force of it is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmd.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what negative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When it is denied. From hence ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the contradiction of Axiomas, when the ſame argument is affirmed or denied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 3.</hi> True and Falſe.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may be a ſecond kinde of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an Axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An Axioma ſecondly is true or falſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When it pronounceth as the thing is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How falſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Contrary.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the affections of a true Axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A true Axioma is contingent or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:150998:44"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>How contingent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When it is ſo true that it may ſometimes be falſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Fortune helpeth the bold; for it may be that which is true to day, to morrow may bee falſe: and therefore the iudgement of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent verity, is called opinion: thoſe things of the time paſt or preſent, may be certaine to a man, but of time to come they cannot by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, although with God all things are preſent. Therefore <hi>Martiall</hi> doth worthily mocke <hi>Priſcus</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Priſcus <hi>thou often askſts what I ſhall be,</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If now moſt rich, hereafter what truely?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Things for to come canst thou not tell them mee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If thou a Lion art, what wilt thou thou be?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>How neceſſary?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When it is alwayes true, neither can be falſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is this affirmative called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This affirmative is called <hi>Katapantòs</hi> of every thing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How impoſible?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Contrarily where it can bee true of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What belongeth to an Axioma of the artes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An axioma of the artes ought to bee <hi>Kantapantòs</hi> as alſo Homogene &amp; Catholique</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is an homogene axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:150998:45"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An homogene axioma is when the parts are eſſentiall among themſelves: as the forme to the thing formed , the ſubiect to its proper adiunct.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>what is this called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> This Genus of the Species is called <hi>Kath' autò</hi> by it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What it a Catholique axioma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Catholique axioma is when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent is alwayes true of the anticedent; not onely in every thing and by it ſelfe, but alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A man is a living creature, reaſonable, number is equall or unequall.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is this called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This is called <hi>Katholon prôton</hi> vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally firſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What then are the lawes of the proper do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments of the artes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe three: the firſt, <hi>Catàpantòs</hi> the law of verity: the ſecond <hi>Kath' autò</hi> the law of iuſtice: the third <hi>Kathòlou prôton</hi> called the law of wiſedome, and ſuch is the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Catholique axiomas, the moſt true &amp; cheife knowledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 4.</hi> The ſimple Axioma.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>You have expounded the common affections
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150998:45"/>of axiomas, the kindes follow, what are then the kindes of an axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An axioma is ſimple or compound.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is ſimple?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Simple is that which is contained in the force of one word; and therefore by an affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative or negative word it affirmeth or deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Fire burneth, fire is hot, fire is not wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew the force of theſe examples?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Here fire is the anticedent, burneth, the conſequent: and this is the firſt diſpoſition of invented things; of che cauſe with the effect, as in the firſt example; the ſubiect with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunct as in the ſecond; the diſagreeing with the diſagreeing, in the third: after a certaine manner, any argument may be enuntiated (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe full of compariſon and diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) agreeings truely by affirming, diſagreeings by denying.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of a ſimple axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A ſimple axioma is generall or ſpeciall.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is generall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Generall is when the common conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent is attributed generally to the common antecedent. and this contradiction, doth not alwayes devide the true &amp; falſe, but both parts of the contingent, as alſo not of contingents may be falſe.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:150998:46"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of the firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A. Eaeh place delighted is, with Baijs pleaſant</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No place delighted is with Baijs pleaſant roomes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of the ſecond?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Every creature is reaſonable, no creature is reaſonable.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a speciall axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A ſpeciall axioma is when the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent is not attributed to every antecedent, and here the contradiction ever divideth the true from the falſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of ſpeciall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Speciall is particular or proper.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is particular?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Particular is when the common conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent is attributed particularly to the antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: but to this axioma it is generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give examples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Somewhat is to be pardoned: Nothing is to be pardoned. Some clemency is not to be prayſed. All clemency is to be prayſed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a proper axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A proper axioma is when the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent is attributed to a proper antecedent.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Fabulla</hi> is faire, whoſe negative &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction is <hi>Fabulla,</hi> is not faire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 5.</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:150998:46"/> The copulative axioma.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the compound axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The compound axioma is that which is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the force of a coniuction. Therefore from an affirmative or negative coniunction it is affirmed or denyed. And a part of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction is true, a part falſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the kindes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A compound Enunciate is for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction congregative, or ſegregative.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is congregatiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Congregative is that which enuntiateth all agreeings by affirmings and diſagreeings by denying.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Copulative or connexed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is copulative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Copulative is that whoſe coniunction is copulatiue.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Eneid:</hi> 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The eaſt and ſouth windes on the ſeas do blow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They ruſh through deepe till on the top they ſhow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The affricke oft with theſe his blaſts conioynes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>This therefore ſhall be the negatiue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The eaſt and ſouth windes not on ſeas doe blow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They ruſh not through the deepe, ne on top ſhow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The affricke doth not oft his blaſts conioyne.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>But whereupon dependeth the judgement of the copulative enunciate?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:150998:47"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The iudgement of the coplative Enun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate being true dependeth of the truth of all parts: falſe, at the leaſt of one part falſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat may further bee compriſed under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The enunciate of a relative quallity is of this kinde, whoſe coniunction is the relation it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Eglog.</hi> 3.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So me thy ſong as ſleepe on graſſe doth queme</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The travailer his weary lims to drench.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew the force of this example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Here the coplative iudgement is as if he ſhould ſay, ſleepe is gratefull to the weary, and ſo thy ſong is pleaſing to me.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the Negative hereof?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Not me thy ſong as ſleep on graſſ doth queme The travailer his weary lims to drench.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 6.</hi> The Connexed Axioma.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is a connexed Axioma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A connexed axioma is congregatiue, whoſe coniection is connexiue.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Eneid.</hi> 2. If fortune doth feigne Simon miſerable, it diſhoneſly feigneth him to bee vaine and a lyer, whoſe negative is if fortune doth not feigne Simon miſerable it diſhoneſly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150998:47"/>feigneth him to be vaine and a liar:</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not this coniunction alſo denyed more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly, by denying the conſequent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Pro Amer.</hi> I am not a murtherer though in their company. <hi>De fato:</hi> Neither if every Enunciation be true or falſe, doth it follow therefore that the cauſes are immutable; For affirmation ſignifieth, if the antecedent be, that the conſequent is alſo. Negation therfore and contradiction determineth if the antecedent be that therefore the conſequent is not. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when thou ſhalt iudge the connexiue to be abſolutely true, thou ſhalt iudge it alſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and thou ſhalt underſtand this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to ſpring from the neceſſary connexion of partes, the which may alſo bee even in falſe partes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. If a man be a Lyon, he is alſo a foure foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, this is a neceſſary connexion.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But if the connexion be contingent, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put for his probability, how ſhall it bee iudged then?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Its iudgment then ſhall be only opinion.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ter:</hi> and <hi>Phamphilus</hi> if thou doſt this, this day is the laſt thou ſhalt ſee mee.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may be further under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This relation connexive of conſequence
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150998:48"/>is like to the connexed axioma, as when <hi>Tulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> is ſaid to be an orrator, hee hath alſo ſkill in pleading well, and thus much of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative axioma.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 7.</hi> The diſcreet Axioma.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is a ſegregative axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. A ſegregatiue axioma is that whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction is ſegregative, and therefore enuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth diſagreeing arguments.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. A ſegregatiue enunciation is diſcreet or diſiunct.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is diſcreete?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Diſcreet is that whoſe coniunction is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretiue, and therefore of diſagreeings it cheifly enunciateth diuerſes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Tuſc.</hi> 5. Although they may be iudged by the force of the body, yet they are referred to the minde: whoſe negatiue and contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, although they may be iudged by the ſence of the body, yet they are referred to the mind, or, although they may be iudged by the ſence of the body, yet they are not referred to the mind. For yet is here a cheife coniunction.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the diſcreet Enunciat iudged to be true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The diſcreete enunciation is iudged to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150998:48"/>be true &amp; lawfull, if the parts be not only true but may be alſo diſcreet.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the falſe or ridiculous iudged?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Contrarily.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 8.</hi> The diſiunct Axioma.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is a diſiunct axioma?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. A diſiunct axioma is a ſegregative axio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma whoſe coniunction is diſiunct.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Georg.</hi> 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There as they ſay is either ſilent night</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alwayes moſt darke and voide of any light,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or elſe the morning from us here doth goe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And brings the day unto them there alſo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Do fato</hi> every enunciation is true or falſe</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Here it ſeemeth is ſignified from the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunct, that one onely is true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. So it is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What ſhall the negative and contradiction bee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Not every enunciation is true or falſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what doth the contradiction ſignifie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. That one of them is not true by neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for if the diſiunction be abſolutely true, it is alſo neceſſary: and the parts of the diſiunct are oppoſite without any meanes.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>But although the diſiunction bee abſolutely
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150998:49"/>and alſo neceſſary may there not be a neceſſity, that the parts ſhould be ſeperately neceſſary?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A man is good or not good, here the diſjunction is neceſſary, and yet a man is good is not a neceſſary enunciation, alſo a man is not good, is not a neceſſary enunciation.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whereupon then dependeth the neceſſity of the diſjunction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The neceſſity of the diſiunction depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on the neceſſary oppoſition, and diſiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the partes, not as their neceſſary veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But is not the diſiunction of tentimes from condition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As if it be though whether <hi>Cleon</hi> will come, or <hi>Socrates,</hi> becauſe it was ſo agreed that one of them onely ſhould come.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>It ſeemeth by this that if the diſjunction be contingent, it is not abſolutely true, but is onely opinionable?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So it is, and that more frequently in the uſe of man.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ovid: Epiſt: Lean.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Either good hap ſhall now unto me fall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or elſe feirce death the end of loving thrall.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:150998:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 9.</hi> The Syllogiſme and its parts.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>You have manifeſted in its ſelfe the axio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall judgement, by axiomas: the dianoeticall followeth, what therefore is dianoia?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Dianoia is when one axioma is derived from another.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the kindes of dianoyia?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Syllogiſme or methode?</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is a Syllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Syllogiſme is a dianoia whereby the queſtion is ſo diſpoſed with the argument, as the antecedent put, it is neceſſarity concluded.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Make this plainer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When the axioma is doubtfull the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is effected, and there is neede of a third argument to bee placed with the queſtion, for its truſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many parts hath the antecedent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The antecedent of a Syllogiſme hath two partes, a propoſition, and an aſſumption.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is a propoſition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A propoſition is the firſt part of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent, whereby the conſequent of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, is at leaſt diſpoſed with the argument.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the aſſumption?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The aſſumption is the ſecond part of the antecedent, which is affirmed from the propoſition.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:150998:50"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what is the conſequent part of the ſyllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The conſequent part of the ſyllogiſme, is that which imbraceth the part of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion and concludeth it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is called from the nature of it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion and concluſion.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>If any part of the ſyllogiſme want, what is ſaid to be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is called <hi>Enthymema.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what if any part happen to be beſides its partes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Then it is called a <hi>Porſyllogiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the order of the partes oftentimes confounded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What then if any doubt ſhall ariſe from it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Then that ſhall be filled up which wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, thoſe cut of which abound: and every part digeſted into his place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 10.</hi> The ſimple contracted ſyllogiſme.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of a ſyllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A ſyllogiſme is ſimple or compound.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is ſimple?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Simple is where the conſequent part of the queſtion is placed in the proportion, the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150998:50"/>antecedent part in the aſſumption.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the affections of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is affirmed, denyed, generall, ſpeciall, and proper.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is it affirmed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From all the affirmative parts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is it denyed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From one negative of the antecedent parts, with complexion.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is it generall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From the generall propoſition and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is it speciall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From one of the generalls onely.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And how is it proper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> From both propers.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the kindes of the ſimple ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſimple ſyllogiſme is contracted by partes, or explicated.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is contract?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Contract is when the argument for the example is ſo ſubjected to a particular queſtion, that the antecedent may bee underſtood to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme each part; and in the aſſumption.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Certaine confidence is vertue, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, certaine confidence is not vertue, as boldnes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew the force of this example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This argument is underſtood to goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150998:51"/>each part of the queſtion, as if it were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, conſtancy is a vertue, and confidence, and therefore certaine confidence is a vertue: alſo boldnes is not a vertue, and yet it is confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and therefore ſome confidence is not a vertue. So in the uſe of diſputing the maſter of the Syllogiſme draweth the judgement, neither is it ſet forth otherwiſe. And this expoſition the beginning of the Syllogiſme is expounded by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſo that the Syllogiſme in its full judgement is more cleare and manifeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 11.</hi> The firſt kinde of the ſimple ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated Syllogiſme.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the explicated Syllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The explicated Syllogiſme whoſe partes are explicated.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the proprieties in this explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Syllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two, firſt the propoſition is generall or proper, ſecondly the concluſion is like to the antecedent or the weaker part.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The kindes are twofold.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The firſt is where the argument alwaies followeth the negative in the other part.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew ſome Syllogiſme of this kinde?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:150998:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> GEN. 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. A troubled man uſeth not his reaſon well:</l>
                  <l>But a wife man uſeth his reaſon well,</l>
                  <l>A wife man is not therefore troubled.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Produce, the example of ſome Orator for this Syllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This judgement is ſo brought forth of <hi>Cicero Tuſc:</hi> 3. And when (ſaith hee) the eye is troubled, it is not honeſtly affected to the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of its duty: and the reſt of the partes, as alſo the whole body, when it is moved from its ſtate, wanteth its office and function, ſo a troubled minde is not honeſtly affected to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill his duty. But the duty of the minde is to uſe reaſon, and a wiſe man is alwayes ſo affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that hee uſeth reaſon moſt excellently; he is therefore never troubled.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of another generall Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> GEN. 2.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres. A mortall thing is compound.</l>
                  <l>A ſoule is not compound.</l>
                  <l>A ſoule therefore is not mortall.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Produce the authority of ſome ancient, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouching this Syllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cicero</hi> judgeth the ſoule to be immortall by this Syllogiſme. <hi>Tuſc:</hi> 1. For wee cannot doubt ſaith hee in our mindes, unleſſe wee bee perchance ignorant in phyſicall things, but that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150998:52"/>there is nothing knit to ſoules, nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, nothing copulate, nothing joyned, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing double; which when it is ſo, can ſurely never be parted, nor divided, nor ſevered, nor drawne aſunder, neither periſh therefore: for periſhing is as it were a departure and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or breach of thoſe parts, which before the periſhing were joyned together.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of a speciall ſyllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> SPEC. 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. A pale man is not couragious.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maximus</hi> is couragious.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maximus</hi> therefore is not pale.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Produce authority for this ſyllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By this judgement <hi>Ovid:</hi> concludeth. <hi>De Pont:</hi> 3. <hi>El:</hi> 3.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Palenes and ſloth are not in the high minde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rather with vipers them on ground we finde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In higheſt things thy minde excels we ſee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No name I finde t'expreſſe the wit of thee.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some miſeries doe taſte, hurt and out worne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Are made to feele ſharpe pricking of the thorne:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet thou art wont to helpe complaning men,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amongſt which number pray let me be then.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew another example of the ſpecial ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> SPEC. 2.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co. A dauncer is <hi>Lecherous.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Murena</hi> is not <hi>Lecherous.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Murena</hi> therefore is no dauncer.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:150998:52"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Produce ſome Orator for this ſyllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cic: pro Mur:</hi> For no man almoſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſober daunceth, unleſſe perchance hee bee mad, neither alone, nor at a moderate and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt banquet; for dauncing is the companion of untimely banquets, pleaſant places, and many delights, thou ſnatcheſt that from me that it is neceſſary that vices ſhould be: thou leaveſt that whereby this removed, this vice ought not to be at all: no filthy banquet, no love, no glotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is ſhewed, and when we finde not all theſe things which have the name of pleaſure, and are vices; there thou canſt not finde lechery, nay thinkeſt thou to finde a ſhadow of luſt in ſuch.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Avouch ſome other authority after the like manner?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> After this manner of judgement <hi>Ovid: de Triſt:</hi> 1. concludeth triply, whil'ſt hee ſets forth the excuſe of his verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They that make verſes ſhould not merry be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our time is clouded with adverſity:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They that write verſes ſhould enjoy their eaſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The ſeas, the windes, with winter fierce me preſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Good poets ſhould not feare, but I feare death,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I dread leaſt ſwordes doe take away my breath:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then what is here, a right judge will admire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If reading them they ſatisfi's deſire.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of proper ſyllogiſmes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> PRO. 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> is not painted by <hi>Apelles.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:150998:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> is painted by <hi>Apelles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> therefore is not <hi>Ageſelaus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example of a proper Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> PRO. 2.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ceſar</hi> oppreſſed his contrey.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tullius</hi> opreſſed not his countrey.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tullius</hi> therefore is not <hi>Ceſar.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 12.</hi> The ſecond kinde of the ſimple explicate Syllogiſme.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſecond kinde of the explicate Syllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſecond kinde of the explicate Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme is, when the argument goeth before in the propoſition, the affirmative followeth in the aſſumption.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of an affirmative gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall after this kinde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> AFF <hi>Gen.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. Every juſt thing is profitable.</l>
                  <l>Every honeſt thing is juſt.</l>
                  <l>Every honeſt thing therefore is profitable</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Produce ſome Orator avouching this Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thus <hi>Cicero</hi> concludeth, <hi>Offic:</hi> 2. The Philoſophers truely with great authority, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150998:53"/>ſoundly and honeſtly, doe diſtinguiſh theſe three confuſed kindes by cogitation. For whatſoever is juſt, that alſo they thinke to be profitable: alſo, whatſoever is honeſt, that is juſt; from whence ariſeth, that whatſoever is honeſt, that is alſo profitable.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of a negative generall Syllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> NEG. GEN.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. A fearefull man is not free.</l>
                  <l>A covetous man is fearefull.</l>
                  <l>A covetous man therefore is not free.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Prove this by ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is thus concluded and judged by <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race: Epiſt:</hi> 1.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who freer is he that as ſervant dwelleth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or he that in his monies love excelleth:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I doe not ſee, he that deſires doth feare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And he that feares his freedome doth not beare.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example of this kinde of Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ten: in Eu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> concludeth and judgeth this, That which is voyd of counſell, cannot be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by counſell.</p>
               <p>Love is voyd of counſell.</p>
               <p>It cannot therefore be governed by counſell.</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Produce the wordes of Terrence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The former Syllogiſme followeth in theſe words: maſter, that thing which hath in it neither counſell nor meanes, that thou canſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150998:54"/>not governe by counſell. In love are all theſe vices, injuries, ſuſpitions, enmities, flatteries, warre, peace againe: theſe uncertaine things if thou wouldeſt guide by certaine reaſon, thou doſt no more then if thou ſhouldeſt labour to to be mad with reaſon.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of the affirmative spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſyllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> AFF. SPE.</p>
               <p>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i. Conſuls made by vertue ought ſtudiouſly to defend the common wealth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> is made Conſul by vertue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> therefore ought ſtudiouſly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the common wealth.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Produce</hi> Tullies <hi>words avouching this ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Orator doth both conclude and judge his owne diligence. <hi>Agr:</hi> 2. For the great care and diligence aſwell of all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, ought to be placed in defending the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, as of thoſe who not in the cradle; but in the campe were made Conſuls: none of our ancients promiſed to the people of <hi>Rome</hi> for mee that I ought to bee truſted: to aske of mee that I ought, even when I did aske, none of our anceſtours commended mee to you, therefore if I neglect any thing, there is none who ſhall intreat mee for you. Yet while my life laſts (I being hee who am able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it from their wickedneſſe) I promiſe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150998:54"/>this to you O <hi>Quirites,</hi> that you have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the common wealth to the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of a good truſt: to a watchfull man, not a coward; to a diligent man, not a ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew another ſyllogiſme of this kinde?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That which comes wiſhed for is grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lesbia</hi> comes wiſhed for to <hi>Catullus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>She is therefore gratefull.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Set forth</hi> Catullus <hi>his wordes wherein he thus concludeth?</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A. That which we long for with deſires great,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is acceptable to us when we heate:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wherefore this gratefull is, more deare then gold,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That</hi> Lesbia <hi>is come our friend of old.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou doſt our wiſhes grant, our hope reſtore;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O light moſt cleare! who is there that is more</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Happy then I, who have what I deſire;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Even what I wiſh ther's nought I can require.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of an negative ſpeciall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> NEG. SPE.</p>
               <p>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o. The deceiver of a loving maid is not to be prayſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demophoon</hi> is the deceiver of a loving maide, to wit <hi>Phyllis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demophoon</hi> therefore is not to bee pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:150998:55"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Set forth the words of</hi> Phillis <hi>in</hi> Ovid <hi>ſo judgeing.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A. It is no glory virgins to deceive,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who love a man and wiſh him for to have;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Simplicity ſhould rather favrur gaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But I that love and al's a woman am.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deceived am by thee with flattering stile,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The gods thy prayſes make it all the while.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of an affirmative pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> AFF. PRO.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Octavius</hi> is <hi>Ceſars</hi> heire.</l>
                  <l>I am <hi>Octavius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I am therefore <hi>Ceſars</hi> heire.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of a negative proper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> NEG. PRO.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Anthony</hi> is not <hi>Ceſars</hi> ſonne.</l>
                  <l>Thou art <hi>Anthony.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou art not therefore <hi>Ceſars</hi> ſonne.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 13.</hi> The firſt connexed Syllogiſme.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>You have expounded hitherto the ſimple Syllogiſme, what now is the compound Syllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The compound Syllogiſme is a Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme where the whole queſtion is another part of the affirmed and compound propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the argument is another part.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:150998:55"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what if any thing were taken away in the compound Syllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That were to put a ſpeciall contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the kindes of a compound Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A compound Syllogiſme is connexed or disjunct.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a connexed ſyllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A connexed ſyllogiſme, is a compound ſyllogiſme, of a connexed propoſition.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many are the manners of diſtinction?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is of two manners.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The firſt manner of the connexed ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme is that which aſſumeth the antecedent, and the conſequent concludeth.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> After this manner <hi>Cicero</hi> concludeth. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>De Divinatione.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>If they be gods it is divination.</l>
                  <l>But they are gods.</l>
                  <l>It is divination therefore.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Offic:</hi> 3. And if alſo nature preſcribeth this, that a man to a man, whatſoever he bee for that ſame cauſe that hee is a man, will uſe conſultation it is neceſſary according to the ſame nature, that the profit of all ſhould bee common. Which if it bee ſo all of us are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in one, and the ſame law of nature; and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150998:56"/>this if it be ſo indeed we are certainely forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the law of nature to violate one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but the firſt is true, the laſt therefore i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo true.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Aeneid:</hi> 4. <hi>Dido</hi> judgeth <hi>Aeneas</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine with her.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Doſt thou me fly by theſe teares I thee pray,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By thy right hand I thee beſeech to ſtay:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elſe thou wilt leave me wretched here alone,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By our deare marriage, our deare love like none.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If I doe ought deſerve if thou haſt beene</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sweet unto me, have pitty on me then:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Looke on thy ſlippery houſe, and now I pray,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If any place for prayers be I ſay:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For</hi> Libians <hi>ſake, for</hi> Nomades <hi>his kings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who hated me and for all other things.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which I for thee did beare, my credits loſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I am alone, for thee thus am I croſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beſides all this, my fame is quite decayed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rather I had my fleſh in duſt were laid.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Doth it alwayes aſſume the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Oftentimes not the ſame but a greater.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cat:</hi> 1. If thy parents feared and hated thee, neither couldeſt thou pleaſe them by any reaſon, in my opinion thou wert to abſtaine a little from their ſight: now the countrey (which is our common parent) hateth and feareth thee, and of a long time judgeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of thee, except it be touching thy death,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150998:56"/>canſt thou neither avoyd its authority, neither follow its judgement, neither feareſt thou its force.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may farther be under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This manner of concluding is the very ſame when the propoſition is a relate of time.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> After this kinde the nymph <hi>O Enon</hi> in <hi>Ovid,</hi> concludeth the error of her fooliſhnes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When</hi> Paris O Enon <hi>hoped to forſake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It would to</hi> Xanthus <hi>with all ſpeede betake:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Xanthus <hi>make haſte returne thou back againe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That ſo this</hi> Paris O Enon <hi>may ſuſtaine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 14.</hi> The ſecond connexive ſyllogiſme.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſecond manner of the connexed ſyllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſecond manner of the connexed ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme taketh away the conſequent that it may take away the antecedent.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If a wiſe man aſſent to any thing, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo he ſhall be opinated.</p>
               <p>Therefore he ſhall aſſent to nothing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the like ſyllogiſme <hi>Ovid: Triſt:</hi> 12. judgeth his fooliſhnes.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:150998:57"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If I were wiſe thoſe ſiſters I ſhould hate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deities hurtfull to whom on them waite:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But now ſo great my fooliſhneſſe is ſeene,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I build them alters whom my hurt have beene.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Theſe two kindes of the ſyllogiſme are moſt uſuall of all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP 15.</hi> The first disjunct ſyllogiſme.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the disjunct ſyllogiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The disjunct ſyllogiſme is the ſyllogiſme compoſed of a disjunct propoſition.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the manners of diſtinction?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The firſt taketh away one and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the reſt,</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Either it is day, or it is night.</p>
               <p>But it is not day?</p>
               <p>It is therefore night.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The judgement of <hi>Cicero</hi> in defence of <hi>Cluventius</hi> is ſuch: But when as this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was propoſed to him, that either he ſhould accuſe juſtly and piouſly, or die ſharpely or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> would rather accuſe after that manner then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> after this.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Make the disjunction appeare clearer?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:150998:57"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Either he muſt accuſe or die.</p>
               <p>He muſt not die,</p>
               <p>He muſt accuſe therefore.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example like to this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is the like reaſoning <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. doſt thou not underſtand it is determined, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thoſe who have done this thing are homi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cides or revengers of liberty? But attend a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and take the thoughts of a ſober man for a little time, and I who am of them, as my ſelfe doth confeſſe, will familiarly argue with thee as a fellow: I deny that there is any meane: I grant that they are, except they be deliverers and conſerveres of the Roman common wealth more then villany, more then homicides, more parricides: if truely it be cruelty, rather to bee a father to the country, then a murtherer of ones ſelfe: Thou art a wiſe and conſiderate man what ſayſt thou: if they be particides, why were they honored of thee, and called to this order by the Roman people why was <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Brutus</hi> by thy meanes freed from the law, if he were abſent more then tenne dayes from the citty? why did <hi>Apolinares</hi> receive <hi>Marcus Brutus</hi> with incredible honour? why was the prouinces given to <hi>Caſſius</hi> and <hi>Brutus,</hi> why were their queſtors added? why were the number of Legates increaſed and this done by thee? they are not therefore homicides. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth then that by thine owne iudgement they are deliverers, when as truely there can be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150998:58"/>no third admitted.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>If the parts of the diſiunct propoſition ſhall be more then two, how ſhall they be iudged then?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The art of iudging them and concluding them ſhall be the ſame.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. So <hi>Cicero</hi> iudgeth <hi>Rabitious</hi> to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the conſulls: And wee ſee (ſaith hee) theſe three to be in the nature of things, to wit that either he ſhould bee with <hi>Saturninus,</hi> or with the good, or that he ſhould lie hid. But to lie hid is proper to the dead and rotten: to be with <hi>Saturninus</hi> of ſury &amp; wickedneſſe: ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and honeſty and ſhamefaſtneſſe conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to be with the conſulls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 16.</hi> The ſecond diſiunct?</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſecond diſiunct?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The ſecond diſiunct, from the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the affirmative aſſumeth one, and taketh away, the reſt.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. It is day or it is night.</p>
               <p>But it is day,</p>
               <p>It is not therefore night.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another example after this manner?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Thus <hi>Iuno</hi> concludeth with <hi>Iove</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Turnus, Aeneid.</hi> 10.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:150998:58"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What if thou ſayeſt the thing thou doſt not meane?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſhould to Turnus give life againe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Now I remaine in miſery and woe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And hope for that which will not happen ſo:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But rather than this ill ſhould come to paſſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I'le mocke my ſelfe and hope paſt hope alas.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew another ſyllogiſme of this kind?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is the like Syllogiſme effected from a propoſition copulative negative, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led negative complexion, and which obtaineth the force of an affirmative diſjunction.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is not both day and night,</p>
               <p>But it is day,</p>
               <p>It is not therefore night.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 17.</hi> The onely method according to <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is method?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Method is a dianoia of diverſe homogene axioma, prepoſed for the clearenes of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from whence the agreeing amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of them are iudged and comprehended in memory.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is to be conſidered in method?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As verity and falſity is beheld in the ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioma conſequence and inconſequence in the ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme, ſo in method it is to be conſidered
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150998:59"/>that by it the more cleare may precede, the more obſcure may follow, and that altogether order and confuſion be iudged.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Make this plainer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> After this manner is diſpoſed from ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogene axiomas in the firſt place by an abſolute notion, the firſt; in the ſecond place the ſecond, in the the third place the third, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>It ſeemeth by this that method doth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually paſſe from vniverſalls to ſingulars?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So it is, for by this ſole and onely way it proceedeth from antecedents altogether, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute notions, to the declaring of unknowne conſequences, and this is the only method that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> taught.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 18.</hi> The firſt illuſtration of methods by illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of artes.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>But doe not examples ſet forth this head more clearely?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, the examples of doctrines and artes doe cheifly demonſtrate and ſet forth the vnity of method, in the which although all the rules are generall &amp; vniverſall, yet the degrees of them are diſtinguiſhed: and by how much every thing ſhall be more generall, by ſo much it ſhal more precede.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:150998:59"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why ſhall the firſt be in the moſt generall place and order?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe in light and knowledge it is firſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why ſhall the ſubalternates follow?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe in their clearenes they are next.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>It ſeemeth by this that thoſe things which by nature are more knowne ſhall precede, thoſe which are leſſe known are ſubiſttute, and at length the moſt ſpeciall follow?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So it is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What then ſhall precede and be firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The moſt general definition ſhal be firſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What ſhall follow?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The diſtribution.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But how if their be many.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Then the partition in perfect partes ſhal precede.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What ſhall follow?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The diviſion into kindes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What then?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The partes themſelves and the kindes are in the ſame order to be handled and defined againe in which they were diſtributed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What further is required?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If there ſhal be a long explication of them they are to be chained together by the chaines of tranſcition.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What benefit redowndeth from hence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It refreſheth and recreateth the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:150998:60"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>But may not example be under this head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Yes as a more familiar thing is taken, ſo a more familiar example muſt bee u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example of what you have here ſhewed out of the art of grammer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All definitions, diſtributions, are found in the rules of grammer, and every one of them ſeverally judged, and all theſe documents in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in diverſe tables, are confounded and mingled together as it were in a certaine port.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What part of dialectica teacheth us to compoſe theſe confuſed rules and digeſt them into order: firſt there is no need of the places of invention, when as they are all found: neither in the firſt iudgement of axiomas, when as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry axioma is proved and valued: neither of the ſecond iudgement of the filogiſme, when as all of them are disputed and concluded controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of ſeveral things by theſe onely ſyllogiſmes: it ſeemeth therefore to bee onely method, is it not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes it is onely method.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is it done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Logitian by this light of artificiall method ſelecteth out of this pott the definition of grammer (for that is moſt generall) and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth it in the firſt place: grammer is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of ſpeaking well. Then hee taketh out of the ſame Oven the particion of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150998:60"/>grammer, and placeth it in the ſecond place: the partes of grammer are two: Etymology and Syntaxis. Then out of the ſame veſſel hee ſeperateth the definition of Etymology of worde, and joyneth it in the third place to thoſe that goe before: then hee ſeeketh out the partes of wordes in letters and ſyllables, and the kindes in wordes of number, and without number, and placeth them with their tranſciti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in their ſeverall places. And ſo the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all the partes of Etymology, together with their diſtributions, colligations, and moſt ſpeciall examples hee placeth in their ſeverall places, and ſo likewiſe in the Syntax. This way all the artes have propoſed to themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 19.</hi> The ſecond example of methode by example of Poets, Orators, Hiſtriographers.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>But is methode onely ſet forth in matter of the artes and doctrines?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, it is alſo declared in all things which we would teach eaſily and plainely: therefore Poets, Orators, and all manner of writers as often as they propoſe any thing to teach to their auditors, doe follow this way, although they doe not enter and inſiſt upon it all alike.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example out of ſome Poet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Virgil</hi> in his Georgicks diſtributeth as I
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150998:61"/>ſaid before the propoſed matter into foure parts, and in the firſt booke followeth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon thinges, as Aſtrology, Meteorology, and of corne and tillage; this was the firſt part of his worke: then the tranſcition is adhibited in the beginning of the ſecond book.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus far of tillage and of ſtarres were we,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Now of the</hi> Bacchus <hi>we'l ſing preſently.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Then hee writeth generally of trees, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſpecially of plants; the ſecond tranſcition is adhibited to the third part, but more imperfect and without an Epilogue. In the beginning of the third booke of Oxen, Horſes, Sheepe, Goates, Dogges.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We'l ſing of goddes</hi> Pales, <hi>al's of him,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who by</hi> Amphryſo <hi>kept his ſheepe moſt trim.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>At length in the beginning of the fourth book there is the third tranſcition of the fourth part, but alſo imperfect from the onely prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of their Bees.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now of the eyre hony Bee I'le ſpeake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So therefore the Poet ſtuddieth to place the moſt generall firſt, the ſubalternate middle, the moſt ſpeciall in the laſt place.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give another poeticall example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ovid: in Faſt:</hi> uſeth this kinde of diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, propoſing in the beginning the ſumme of his worke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I'le ſing of times that paſſe throughout the yeare, Fall of the ſtarres and riſing I'le declare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By and by having made imploration hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termineth
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150998:61"/>the partition of the yeare made firſt by <hi>Tumulus</hi> into ten monethes, which hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When as</hi> Romes <hi>builder did the yeare devide, In it he made five moneths and five beſide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And a little after hee adjoyneth <hi>Numa</hi> his more full deviſor.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But</hi> Numa <hi>neither</hi> Ianus <hi>did omit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nor yet the ancient ſhadowes out did put:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But to th'old monethes two more appointed he.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Here the Poet having interpreted the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon differences of holy-dayes, working-dayes, banquet-dayes, kalends, nones, ides, at the laſt hee followeth every moneth in his place, and with a preface after this order he paſſeth from generalls to the ſtudy of ſpecialls.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ith what I have you ſhewed what theſe things be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It now remaines, we part them preſantly.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>At length after the expoſition of every part the tranſcition is joyned as in the end of the firſt and beginning of the ſecond booke.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The firſt part of my taske is ended now,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The moneth is done, my little booke alſo:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ianus <hi>is done, another moneth beginneth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Another booke now with that moneth reneweth.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>And in every one of his bookes afterward the tranſcitions are adhibited, but leſſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How doe the Orators follow this methode?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Orators in poems, narrations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmations, perorations doe follow this order
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150998:62"/>as the nature both of the art and the order of the thing doe require, and ſometimes more ſtudiouſly too.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give example?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Cicero</hi> in an accuſation firſt by propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, then by parting, followeth this order. <hi>Queſtor Cn: Paxeris</hi> ſaith he, thou haſt beene Confull unto this time fourteene yeares, and from that day unto this day in which thou haſt made me, I call thee into judgement; there was no voyd houre found in robbery, wickedneſſe, cruelty, iniquity. This is the propoſition &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the chief matter, as in this judgement moſt generall. The partition followeth: theſe are the yeares conſume in the queſtorſhip, end a Sciatican embaſſage, and the Vrban pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip, and in the Sicilian pretorſhip: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this ſhall bee the fourefold diſpoſition of my accuſation, which foure partes with their particular partitions hee hath alſo handled in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir ſeverall order and place, and coupled them with tranſcitions; the three firſt in the third booke. Wherefore (ſaith he) his queſtorſhip being ſhewed, &amp; his firſt magiſtracy, together with his theft and wickedneſſe looked unto, let us attend to the reſt. Then having expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the faults of his embaſſadorſhip, the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcition to his pretorſhip followeth. But let us now come to that famous pretorſhip, and thoſe faults which were more knowne to thoſe which were preſent, then to us who come me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:150998:62"/>and prepared to pleading. This tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcition is more imperfect without an epilogue: at length in the beginning of the fourth oration there is the like tranſcition to the fourth part of the Sicilian pretorſhip. Many neceſſary things O Iudges I muſt pretermit, that I may in ſome manner ſpeake of thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things which are committed to my truſt, for I have received the cauſe of <hi>Sicilia,</hi> that province hath drawne me unto this buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example out of ſome Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Livy</hi> doth ſo imbrace the ſumme of ſeventy yeares in the beginning, then divideth them by tennes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 20.</hi> The ſecrets of method.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>It ſeemeth that in the diverſe axiomaticall homogens, as alſo in the judgement of the ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme, the notes of methode ſhall be as often as any thing is taught clearely: but is there no other kinde of methode?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, when as the auditor ſhall be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in a certaine part with, delectation and a greater motion, then certaine homogens are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, as the lights of definition, partition and tranſcition: and certaine heterogens are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as digreſſions from the matter, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morations upon the thing; but chiefly the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of thinges in the beginning is turned over,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150998:63"/>and certaine antecedents are put after conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents. Therefore to that rule of perfect me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod this may ſeeme ſomewhat more imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; the forme is not onely lame, things being detracted; or abounding, things being added; but alſo the order of it being inverted by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine degrees is prepoſterous.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Give an example of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The like the Poet maketh with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine greater kinde of artificialnes, while hee propoundeth to himſelfe to leade the people. <hi>viz.</hi> the beaſt like heads of the multitude, and therefore hee deceiveth diverſe wayes, hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth in the middle, and there oftentimes he comprehendeth the firſt, to conclude the laſt, he placeth in an uncerca ne and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought of chance. So as (<hi>Horace</hi> ſaith) <hi>Homer</hi> diſpoſeth his Iliads.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ne doth this man</hi> Troyes <hi>warres divide ſo well,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He alwayes maketh haſte the vent to tell:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Even in the midſt reader he doth catch,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leaves off his tract, with haſte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it doth ſnatch,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And thus he lies, thus mingles falſe with true,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So that ne first nor midſt in it I view.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Q. <hi>Proceed to further examples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So <hi>Virgil</hi> taketh <hi>Aeneas</hi> from <hi>Sicilia,</hi> and makes a narration of him in the banquet of <hi>Carthage;</hi> and at laſt bringeth in his diverſe troubles. So the commedian Poets, although with great judgement they have diſtinguiſhed their Comedies by acts and ſeenes yet doe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150998:63"/>ſo effect, that all thinges ſeeme to be done by chance. The Orators attribute all to victory. Therefore this ſeemeth to be placed chiefly by them not ſo much to teach as to perſwade, when as alſo thoſe things which doe equally excell, are kept even unto the laſt, and the meanes are conferred into the middle, according to <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> diſpoſition.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:150998:64"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:150998:64"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
